Hello, today we will be talking
about dynamically walking robots.
We'll go over what is walking,
why is it useful for legged robots.
And introduce a simple walking
model called the rimless wheel.
This rimless wheel is a special
type of model called a template.
Templates are a special class
of models that represent
the simplest models that are needed
to describe a target behavior.
We'll show that templates can give design
insights into building legged robots, and
then by building the rimless wheel
template into our walking motion of
the mechanical system we can get a robot
to walk robustly with minimal computation.
So before we get into walking
let's take a step back and
talk about locomotion in general.
Robots and animals move through
their environments by generating
forces on their environments.
For example, when you run,
your leg pushes downwards and
backwards, creating a downwards and
backwards force on the environment.
Through Newton's Third Law, a reaction
force is created upwards and forwards.
Newton's Second Law then causes
an acceleration which gives you movement.
Biologists studying legged locomotion have
shown that the methods animals use to
generate forces on their
environment are extremely diverse.
For example, the number of legs, and
the shapes of legs of
the animals varies tremendously.
Humans have two legs, whereas millipedes,
have approximately 200.
Hedgehogs have relatively short legs,
while spiders have very long,
and thin legs.
But, biologists have also discovered
that the actual forces generated
by these diverse strategies
are remarkably similar.
For example, when ground reaction
forces are measured in running
they generally follow
the same basic force profile.
A human running on two legs and
a dog trotting on four legs
can look very similar based on the ground
reaction forces they generate.
They're even similar to cockroaches
running with an alternating tripod gate
with six legs.
And even crabs running
sideways with eight legs.
So biologists have proposed two basic
mechanisms to describe these four
profiles generated during walking and
running.
The forces generating during
walking tend to appear
as a mass vaulting over
a relatively stiff leg.
Forces generated during running tend to
look like a mass bouncing on a spring
much like a pogo stick.
These mechanisms have important features
that are relevant for robot design.
For example, both mechanisms involve
some way of retaining a portion
of the mechanical energy of the previous
stride to use in the next stride.
Also by analyzing simple
models of these mechanisms,
we can make statements
about their stability.
So let's take a closer look at walking,
which is the focus of this lecture.
We can gain insight into the mechanism
behind walking by looking
into its energetics.
So a distinctive feature of walking is
the kinetic energy, which is the energy of
motion, oscillates out a phase with
gravitational potential energy.
Which is the energy due to gravity.
When a leg touches down and
a body moves forwards in the beginning
of a walking stance, the body uses it's
kinetic energy to vault upwards and
over the leg in the first half of stance.
This process converts some kinetic energy
into gravitational potential running
energy during the second half of stance.
Starting when the leg is vertical,
this gravitational potential
energy is converted back into kinetic
energy as the body is pulled forwards and
downwards by gravity,
accelerating the body.
This process repeats itself
when the next leg touches down.
This process of exchanging kinetic and
gravitational potential energy can be
very efficient especially at low speeds.
Animals have been measured
to conserve up to 70% of
their mechanical energy while walking.
Energy efficiency is important for
legged robots because it allows us to
build robots that potentially move faster,
operate for
longer durations, and don't have to
carry as much fuel or battery weight.
The type of walking we have been talking
about so far is called dynamic walking.
Where the robot is not perfectly
balanced during stance.
As you may have seen in videos,
many robots also walk by a different
mechanism called quasi-static walking.
In quasi-static walking,
the robot is nearly balanced
throughout its entire walking stride,
and undergoes minimal accelerations.
Because accelerations are minimal
in quasi-static walking,
it is typically quite slow.
Although quasi-static motions
in general have there use,
we will focus only on dynamic
motions in this lecture and
course due to their potential to make
robots faster and more efficient.
Now that we have identified a mechanism
of locomotion, how do we model it?
There are many ways to model locomotion,
from simulations involving thousands of
variables to ones that are quite simple.
Overly complex models can fall victim
to what is called Bellman's curse of
dimensionality, where the amount of
computation time or data points needed for
analysis, increases exponentially
with the number of variables.
On the other hand,
extremely simple models can be too limited
to capture the full complexity
of the desired behavior.
To address this tension between simplicity
and complexity, roboticists and
biologists have developed a modeling
framework called templates and
anchors to capture both the simplicity of
the underlying mechanism of locomotion and
its complexity in a physical system.
Templates are the simplest model needed
to describe the target behavior.
For example, with running and walking
templates could be models representing
the underlying mechanisms
observed in biology.
Because they have no more states or
parameters than necessary, templates can
capture what is fundamentally going on
in a movement in it's most simple form.
This simplicity makes templates very
beneficial for analysis and control.
Anchors, on the other hand,
are more elaborate models than incorporate
the important degrees of
freedom of a physical system.
For example,
when modeling a hopping kangaroo,
an anchor might take into
account the leg joints.
The template then describes the motion
of the kangaroo through the anchor.
By trimming away the degrees of freedom,
a template
might consist of a simple bouncing mass
on a spring to describe the kangaroo.
This relationship between templates and
anchors is very important.
A template is only valid
if it in some sense
is a version of the anchor
with fewer degrees of freedom.
In which case, we say that the anchor
embeds the template dynamics.
And then if the template is anchored to
the physical system through the anchoring.
This relationship can also facilitate the
control of robots as control policies at
the simple template level can then be
mapped in a more complex anchor level.
For example, the control of the template
can be used to guide the control of
the individual robot joints.
To illustrate how useful templates
can be for low level robot control,
we're going to look at a model
that we consider a template for
walking called the rimless wheel.
The rimless wheel has historical
significance as it was
one of the models Tad McGeer, then
a professor at Simon Treasure University,
used in analyzing his walkers
powered entirely by gravity,
in his famous 1990 paper titled
Passive Dynamic Walking.
The rimless wheel is a relatively
simple dynamical system,
representing a spoked wheel
with its rim removed.
This template also incorporates
an important aspect of legged locomotion,
a power source.
Gravity pulls the rimless wheel down
an incline ramp, accelerating the model
over the course of a stride and
allowing it to walk on its spokes.
The fact that gravity is the power
source instead of electricity
isn't that important as we will see that
a small amount of constant work done by
gravity each stride can be replaced by
motors to generate powered robot walking.
It might not be immediately obvious,
however,
most wheels capture walking behavior.
A rimless wheel walking down a ramp is
a lot like a wheel rolling down a ramp,
much like you probably studied
in your first physics course.
In a rolling motion with a normal wheel,
gravity is accelerating the center of
mass downwards, causing a movement
around whatever point the wheel is
currently touching the ground with.
This moment around the ground contact
point accelerates the wheel down the ramp.
This ground contact points on
the wheel touch the ground only for
an instant before lifting off again.
So what happens when we
give the wheel spokes and
then take away the rim of the wheel?
Well, if there's an internet or
very large number of spokes
then almost nothing changes.
We get rolling behavior or
something very similar to it.
But as we take away the number of spokes,
the center of mass has a more pronounced
vault over the point where the spoke
contacts the ground, and the kinetic and
gravitational potential energy oscillate
out of phase with greater amplitude.
We've arrived at a very
simple model of walking.
In our model,
the spoken contact with the ground
represents the leg in
contact with the ground.
As one leg lifts off,
another instantaneously touches down so
that the body represented by the center of
mass always has a leg in ground contact.
Of course, a rimless wheel doesn't
look entirely like a biped.
Maybe it reminds you more of a tumbleweed.
But if we choose to visually ignore the
spokes not in contact with the ground, and
instead pretend that there's another
leg recirculating to prepare for
the next step, we have a convincing
picture of how this model
can represent a biped walking
with what we call a compass gait.
The version of the rimless wheel,
that we are discussing today,
only has one degree of freedom,
which is the wheel angle.
And six parameters which are the mass,
how far the mass is distributed from the
mass center, the leg length, the inter-leg
angle, the ramp angle, and finally,
the vertical acceleration due to gravity.
The rimless wheel template is a simple
enough model to analyze mathematically.
But we will forego
the mathematical analysis, and
instead rely on physical intuition
with a 3D printed wheel model.
So what does it take for
our rimless wheel model to walk?
Over a level ground,
in the absence of a source of energy,
the model quickly comes to a stop due
to the legs impacting the ground.
Because the leg impacts involve
mass coming sharply to a stop,
which results in a loss of kinetic energy.
This, of course, is in contrast
to a wheel rolling down a ramp
which can accelerate for quite some time
before being slowed down by friction.
This illustrates an important concept
in legged locomotion which is that
legged locomotion is fundamentally and
energetically a dissipative process.
As you can see, it only takes a small
amount of gravitational potential energy,
provided by a slight ramp incline, for
the model to walk at a steady speed.
From stride to stride, the mass center
of the rimless wheel gets lower and
lower as it travels down the ramp.
This change in height is constant for
each stride.
So, during each stride approximately
the same amount of gravitational potential
energy is being added to the model
which is converted into kinetic energy.
This kinetic energy is then lost
when the leg impacts the ground.
This process then repeats giving us
the repetitive behavior that we see.
If we tilt the ramp up more, more energy
is added and the template walks faster.
If we lower the ramp less energy is added
for stride and the template walks slower.
The fact that the model walks with such
a small ramp angle, just that walking like
a rimless wheel is quite energetically
efficient despite the losses involve.
And in a minute, we will see that using
a modern of gravity to add the small
amount of fix energy per stride on
a robot retains this efficiency property.
Aside from the efficiency of the motion,
there is another important
feature at play here.
There is actually an advantage to legged
locomotion being a lossy process, and
that is because it allows legged
locomotion to be mechanically stable.
Notice, that if we roll
a wheel down the ramp,
the speed of the wheel
increases as it rolls.
But not so with our legged template.
This is because the energetic
losses naturally regulate
the speed of the system.
Odic will go into more detail about
this during his anchor lectures.
But the intuitive idea here is that
the energetic losses from the leg impacts
increases with velocity, which slows down
the template if it gets moving too fast.
However, if the template is to slow
these impact losses are small and
the constant amount of energy added per
stride by gravity speeds the system up.
Eventually the system reaches a periodic
limit cycle, a steady rolling speed.
Stability is an incredibly important
topic in leg and robots, and
we will continue to come back
to it during this course.
So why is it important that our
walking template is stable?
One reason is that if we build robots
that passively anchored a template
through their mechanical design,
it allows us to build robots that walk
stably with little to no computation.
This is Tad McGuire's famous
passive dynamic walker.
The robot is purely mechanical, it has
no computer, no motors, and no sensors.
And yet, it can walk down a ramp in a
manner that is shockingly anthropomorphic.
Instead of being programmed on a computer,
the control scheme is designed into
the mechanism, in much the same way
as it is with the rimless wheel.
Because the underlying template
behavior is stable and
has been mechanically encoded or
anchored in the machine.
It is able to walk a non-trivial
duration without falling over
at a nearly constant speed, despite the
model being an imperfect representation
of the physical world, as all models are.
As we have said before, a robot can walk
like a rimless wheel using only a small
amount of motor energy instead of gravity.
Andy Marina,
a professor at Cornell University,
did just that with his robot
called the Cornell ranger.
In 2011, the Cornell ranger was able
to walk an ultra marathon of 40.5
miles non-stop on a single battery
charge of less than 500 watt hours,
or about $0.05 worth of electricity.
By creating a robot that is close to
a literal instantiation of an efficient
locomotion model, Angie Rerina was
able to more than double the previous
distant record for robotic legged
locomotion on a single battery charge.
Robots can also mechanically
encode templates without literally
instantiating them.
For example, the REX robot walks with
a motorized alternating tripod gait
that has rimless wheel dynamics in the
forward direction, while the tripod and
support allows the robot to be very
balanced in the other directions,
much like a three-legged chair.
This stability of both the template and
the anchor allows Rex to walk robustly
over a wide variety of terrains,
even rocky slopes and mountains, with
almost no control at the computer level.
Instead, the robot interacts with, and
responds to changes in the environment at
the mechanical level, which is possible,
because the primary dynamical effects can
be modeled as a mechanically
stable template.
In this lecture,
we discussed what biologists have found
to be a mechanism behind dynamic walking.
That walking can be approximated
by the pendular dynamics
of a mass vaulting over
its relatively stiff leg.
We've formulated a low
degree of freedom model for
this mechanism, called the rimless wheel.
This model is simple enough to analyze and
provide insight,
yet complex enough to capture general
principles including efficiency and
self-stabilizing behavior in
the presence of a power source.
And we saw that by embedding the template
dynamics into a physical robot,
engineers can build machines
that can walk without computers,
as well as make robot marathoners and
mountain climbers.
Next lecture we'll focus on templates for
running and
we'll see that running can be described
using pendular dynamics as well.
When the relatively stiff leg
is replaced with a spring leg.