Last lecture we investigated walking
using a pendulum-like template.
In this lecture we will learn about
templates used to describe the mechanics
of running.
We will see why running is an important
mode of robotic locomotion,
its advantages over walking, and that
biologists have shown that running can
often be approximated by the dynamics
of the bouncing spring mass system,
much like hopping on a pogo stick.
Finally, we will show how running
templates can be anchored into
mechanics of robots so that they are able
to run robustly with minimal computation.
Why is running an important
mode of robotic locomotion?
If we can build robots that walk well,
why wouldn't we just design
robots to walk really fast?
Well, running is important because walking
becomes inefficient at high speeds.
Intuitively, we could see in the last
lecture that with our walking model,
that the energetic losses of impacts
when walking with a stiff leg
quickly increase with speed.
Instead of a stiff leg,
running involved using a relatively much
springier leg which reduces these impacts.
Another reason for running is that
there's a speed limitation for
walking with pendular-like dynamics.
During walking, gravity is the only force
accelerating the mass center downwards.
But the mass center follows a circular
trajectory during the pendulum
like motion, so
there is a centripetal acceleration
of the mass center towards the tail.
If this centripetal acceleration exceeds
the acceleration that gravity can provide,
then the normal force at the foot
against the ground will go to zero.
With your normal force, a leg isn't
able to generate forces on the body.
The centripetal acceleration divided
by the acceleration due to gravity
is equal to what is known
as Froude's number.
Simplifying to velocity squared divided
by the quantity of acceleration due to
gravity times the leg length.
Biologists predict that walking cannot
occur with a Froude number greater than 1.
Most animals, however,
are observed transitioning from a walk
to a run well before a Froude number 1.
For example, many bipeds,
including humans and birds,
are observed transitioning to a run
with a Froude number of about 0.5,
with the hypothesis being that they do so
to choose the most energetically gait.
For these same reasons,
running is an important and
necessary form of locomotion for robots
that move with a higher Froude number.
Biologists have shown that the forces
generated against the ground while running
often appear to have the same force
profile as a hopping spring-mass system.
These observed forces have been measured
to be remarkably similar between animals
with widely different sizes,
leg numbers, postures, and morphologies.
Despite the very different ways
that animals generate these forces.
In this motion, the mass center height
decreases in the first half of the stance.
Reaches it's lowest point mid
stance as if compressing a spring.
And then increases in the second half
of the stance as if releasing a spring.
We refer to the spring mass
like dynamics of running
as the spring loaded pendulum model.
Where a leg or
set of legs in contact with the ground can
be approximated by a single spring leg.
There are many variations of
a spring-loaded pendulum mechanism,
some of which have proved to be very
useful as templates for roboticists.
This theme of modeling leg of locomotion
as a pendulum continues with running.
Because during each stance, the center of
mass is interacting with the ground for
a leg much like the mass on a pendulum
acts through its base through a link.
However, unlike walking, we have
the added leg compliance in the form
of a spring to store and
release energy from stride to stride.
This spring is important because
like in elastic bouncing ball,
many running organisms in robots
store potential energy during stance,
to improve the energetic
efficiency of their gait.
For example, using tendons or
tendon-like mechanisms.
Animals appear to run in the spring loaded
pendulum dynamics in many directions,
not just forwards and backwards.
As we live in three dimensional space,
there are three planes of motion
available to move through.
These planes have anatomical
names relative to
the center of the organism or robot.
The Sagittal plane divides an organism
into left and right halves.
The Coronal plane divides an organism
into front and rear halves.
And the Transverse plane divides
an organism into top and bottom halves.
Locomotion can occur in all three planes,
but often it is useful to examine or
approximate motion in a single plane.
The Sagittal plane is probably
what we are most familiar with,
as many animals run predominantly
in a Sagittal plane.
However, running also
occurs in also planes.
Crabs are notable Coronal plane runners,
and
many organisms such as cockroaches run
primarily in the Transverse plane.
For the rest of the lecture we'll focus
on two templates that are variants
of the spring loaded pendulum.
The spring loaded inverted pendulum, or
slip model includes the presence of
ballistic flight between stance events and
is commonly used to describe Sagittal and
Coronal plane running.
The lateral leg spring or
LLS model involves switching between
alternating sides of leg ground contact.
The LLS model is commonly used to
describe transverse plane running.
The Spring Loaded Inverted Pendulum or
SLIP template is given by a point mass
attached to the ground by a masses
spring leg in the presence of gravity.
Often in biology, SLIP running can be
seen in the Sagittal and Coronal planes.
During stance, SLIP generates the familiar
spring-loaded pendulum forces
seen in biological running.
When stance is complete,
the system lifts off the ground and
it undergoes ballistic flight.
The leg angle is changed in flight to
prepare for the next touchdown event.
And when that spring leg touches down
again the process repeats itself.
There are many variances
to this SLIP template.
Different spring models can be used,
for example a linear hook slide spring.
Friction can be neglected or
taken into account as well as actuation.
Typically SLIP is controlled by
either choosing the appropriate
legging on flight, or by formulating
actuated version of the model to
apply forces of torques and stance.
Although we have it shown here for
simplicity, SLIP often takes into account
the pitch angle of the mass center.
The SLIP template is much more complex
than the rimless wheel template for
a few reasons.
One is that is there are more
degrees of freedom even when
pitch isn’t taken into account.
In stance and flight the mass is free
to move in two directions instead of
one as with the rimless wheel.
Another is that
the equations of motion for
SLIP take the form of
a hybrid dynamical system.
There are two hybrid states,
stance and flight.
Each with it's own equations of
motion governing the dynamics.
The transition from stance to
flight occurs when the leg
reaches it's rest length with
a positive radial velocity.
Although transition from flight to stance
occurs when the leg contacts the ground.
Physically accurate hybrid dynamical
systems can be very complex, and
typically are much more difficult to
analyze than non-hybrid dynamical systems.
But despite their complexity,
hybrid systems offer a natural choice for
modelling leg of locomotion, due to the
changing dynamics depending on if a leg is
in contact with the ground or not.
Unfortunately, no analytic
solution existS for
the equations in motion
describing dynamics of SLIP.
So, it's not possible to
get a close form expression
describing the position of the mass
center as a function of time.
This is because the class
of differential equations,
which can be solved analytically,
is very small.
And no such solution exists for
the stance dynamics here.
We can, however,
perform numerical analysis of SLIP and
apply mathematical tools to qualitatively
describe the behavior of this system,
which can be quite insightful.
If we as roboticists need analytic
solutions governing the equations of
motion, often we can make approximations
to the system to achieve our goals.
Several techniques, such as making
small angle approximations to linearize
the sines and cosines, assuming that
gravity acts radially instead of downwards
in stance, or
outright ignoring gravity during stance,
can be used to get closed form expressions
of the state from stride to stride.
Interestingly even though we are,
in effect,
making an approximation
to win approximation,
this can work quiet well and practice
use for controlling robots to run.
As long as the state stays
within the operating regime or
this assumption are approximately valid.
The body and legs of the Rex Robot in
many ways embodied the slip template.
Rex has six C shaped springy legs that can
interact with the ground in unison to
make the center of mass trajectory
look like it's under the influence
of a single spring leg.
By using three legs at once in
an alternating tripod gait,
Rex is able to run with SLIP like
dynamics in the Sagittal plane
while passably being very balanced.
Due to the tripod of support preventing it
from falling over In any one direction,
much like a three-legged chair.
In this video, the computer on
Rex isn't using any sensors,
aside from the motor encoders, to run.
It's just spinning the motors and letting
the natural slip-like dynamics occur.
Here the naturally stable dynamics of
the robot body directly interact with
the environment,
minimizing the computation
needed at the onboard computer.
Might even say that the computation has
been offloaded to the mechanical design to
act like an analog computer.
This is important, because it makes
the behavior of Rex not dependent on
sensors measuring
the external environment, or
some programmed internal
model of the world.
Rex can run with the stable gait using
minimal computation just by anchoring
the SLIP template.
Another important template is called
the Lateral Leg Spring or LLS model, and
is often used to model
running in a transfers plane.
In this template the dynamics are governed
by the familiar spring loaded pendulum.
However, once the leg on one side of the
body lifts off, a leg in the other side of
the body touches down at the same
instant generating side to side motion.
Like the SLIP,
many different variants of LLS exists.
For example, the heading angle
of the body can be included and
the legs can connect to the body at
points offset from the center of mass.
It turns out that the side
to side motion generated by
LLS can be very stable
with the right parameters.
It is hypothesized that this
mechanical stability could
explain the stability
of cockroaches running.
Where cockroaches are able
to react to environmental
perturbations faster then
would be possible for
a neurological signal to go from the leg
to the brain, be processed, and go back.
Instead, it is thought that the control
system is partially built-in
to the mechanism in the cockroach,
much like how his template can
be anchored into a robot design.
The DynaClimber Robot is
a robotic climber that runs
vertically with LLS-like dynamics.
Like Rex, the DynaClimber's mechanical
design provides stability for
its motion, allowing it to run up a wall
with little sensing or computation.
Today we've seen that
the mechanics of running can
often be captured by the mechanism
of a spring-loaded pendulum which
generates the same ground reaction profile
as created by many biological runners.
Running is an important
mode of locomotion for
legged robots, because it is more
efficient than walking at high speeds.
And because walking like
a pendulum with a stiff leg
can't occur at a Froude
number of greater than one.
We've seen that running can
occur in different directions,
not simply the Sagittal plane.
Most importantly,
the dynamics of running templates can be
anchored into legged robots, allowing them
to run in a variety of directions with
little to no computation or sensing.
Using their natural dynamics instead for
stability and to passively balance.
Next lecture, we will finish our section
on templates by examining the class
of running robots that use the underlying
dynamics of SLIP to actively balance.