In the last few lectures, we learned
about templates and their importance for
robot design and control.
Some of the examples we
saw included walking and
running robots that anchored the stability
properties of their templates directly in
their mechanical design,
in a way that they could move robustly
with almost no sensing or computation.
In this lecture,
we'll discuss the case where more active
control is needed not to fall over.
Specifically, we'll look at the ideas
pioneered by Mark Reinert in 1980s,
during his professorship at
the Carnegie Mellon University and
the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
In this lecture we will learn about his
machines and view them through the lens of
controlling a spring-loaded,
inverted pendulum template.
The mechanical design of Raibert's
hopper is facilitated their control.
The sagittal plane hopper, which we first
investigate, was fixed to a boom and
possessed three degrees of freedom,
allowing it to move vertically,
horizontally and to pitch.
The leg was radially actuated by
a pneumatic actuator, which also provided
the leg with compliance in
a similar fashion to a spring.
Hydraulic actuators
controlled the leg angle.
The leg was also light enough to be
able to swing without significantly
disrupting the body dynamics.
So the mechanical design of Raibert's
hopper is pretty closely approximated
in the actuated version of slip.
Raibert's idea was to
separately control for
hopping height, forward speed in flight,
and pitch angle.
Of course, all three of these things
are coupled through the dynamics,
but Raibert recognized that these
coupling effects were weak enough so
that stable running could be
achieved despite their interaction.
To control hopping height,
a fixed magnitude radial force is applied
during stance with a pneumatic actuator.
And the duration of this thrust force is
modulated to achieve the desired height.
As the mechanical losses from friction and
impacts monotonically
increase with hopping height,
there is a unique equilibrium height for
each thrust duration and stance.
Thus to jump higher, a longer thrust
duration is used and vice versa.
The body pitch is controlled by
actuating the leg angle and stance.
The pitch angle can be sensed using
an inertial measurement unit, and
a proportional derivative
controller is used to derive
the system to the desired pitch angle.
We will talk more about proportional
derivative control in a later lecture,
but for now the intuition is that
the leg motors are given a torque
command proportional to the pitch error,
or
a difference between the desired and
the actual pitch to decrease this error.
But before the torque command is set,
it is subtracted from by a value
proportional to angular velocity.
This term is used in an effort to
slow down the angular velocity so
that the desired pitch isn't
continuously overshot.
So in stance, radio actuation controls for
hopping height, while angular
actuation controls your pitch.
Since there are only two degrees of
freedom of actuation of forward in stance,
how can forward speed be controlled?
This is where things get interesting.
Instead of controlling
forward speed in stance,
forward speed is controlled in flight
by choosing the light touchdown angle.
This is an example of where the
inheritantly hybrid dynamics of leg and
locomotion can be leveraged for
controlling robots.
Let's stop for a minute and consider why
the light touchdown angle is important.
To do so, we're going to go back to the
dynamics of a purely passive slip model.
If the model is released from some
height with some set forward speed,
then the leg touch standing will
determine what happens in stance
by setting up how much gravity pulls the
inverted pendulum forwards or backwards.
Intuitively, the more negative
the leg angle is at touchdown,
then the more the model's forward
acceleration will increase.
The more positive the leg
angle at touch down,
the more the model's forwards
acceleration will decrease.
Because the dynamics don't
have an analytic solution,
the precise net acceleration in
stance as a function of leg angle,
doesn't have an analytic expression.
However, we can intuit that the leg touch
down angle is monotonic with the net
forwards acceleration.
A consequence of this is that there is
a unique leg angle that will give no net
acceleration direct stance.
When this leg angle is chosen,
we call the distance that the foot lands
in front of the body the neutral point.
At the neutral point, the mass slows down
in the first half of the stance, but
then speeds up in the second half
of the stance by the same amount.
By estimating the neutral point and
choosing to touch down with the foot
in front or behind the neutral point,
we can affect a net acceleration in
stance to regulate forward speed.
We don't have an extremely accurate way
of estimating the neutral point, but
it turns out that a very
crude estimation can suffice.
Here's how it's done.
We know that landing with a foot at the
neutral point is zero net acceleration.
The forward distance traveled in stance is
then equal to the average stance velocity
times the time spent in stance.
The neutral point is half of this
forward's distance traveled.
We can use the estimated forward
speed in flight as a proxy for
the average forward speed in stance, and
use the measured previous stance time as
an estimate for the next stance time.
Now that we have a way of
estimating the neutral point,
we can regulate speed by landing
with an offset to the neutral point.
To accelerate, a leg angle was chosen that
places the foot behind the neutral point
and vice versa.
Despite all of these approximations, the
Raibert controller works quite well and
can produce impressive behaviors.
Shown here is a two-legged version of
Raibert's hopper running a controller,
where one leg hops while
the other circulates.
Raibert also built an unconstrained
version of this robot not supported in any
direction.
This robot has the same
radial actuation as before.
But now, two motors capable of
applying torques in two different
direction of leg angle.
It is controlled by a direct extension
of his sagittal plane controllers.
Again, he divided the control problem
into that of controlling hopping height,
horizontal velocity in flight,
and posture.
To control the new degrees of freedom,
he simply used copies of his sagittal
plane controller for each direction.
Now our neutral point is a two-dimensional
position vector, and the x and
y offsets from the neutral point are each
individually determined from the x and
y speeds.
The posture now consists of a pitch and
a roll angle, which are individually
controlled by the two angular hip motors.
This simple controller
extension allowed for
a free running robot, capable of feats
that are still impressive today.
The robots Raibert built were
not just limited to monopeds.
He was able to apply the same control
ideas to robots with multiple legs,
by using the concept of a virtual leg.
When multiple legs act in unison,
touching down and
lifting off roughly at the same time,
it can act as a single virtual leg.
The forces and torques on the body by
this virtual leg, are simply the sum of
the forces and torques acting on
the body by the multiple legs.
By applying the previous
controllers to the virtual leg, and
getting the actual legs to have the same
combined effect as a virtual leg,
the robot can run with
a variety of different gaits.
Now we should note that one reason
these robot behaviors are so
visually striking is that they
have an off-board power source.
We will see in later lectures that a robot
needing to carry its own power source
can significantly increase the robot's
weight and hurt performance.
Even so, Raibert's robots
continue to impress to this day.
We consider a contributing factor to
the success that the mechanical design
of the robots facilitated their control.
By building a robot that naturally
anchored a slip template through either
an almost literal instantiation
of the template or
being capable of acting
like a virtual monoped.
Raibert's idea to control for hopping
height and pitch angle using the leg
motors and stance, and forward speed using
the natural hybrid dynamics of slip by
regulating the touch down offset from
a neutral point, is a great example of
leveraging the natural hybrid
dynamics of legged locomotion.
In this section on templates,
we've seen that robotic legged locomotion
is achieved by properly regulating
leg forces on the environment.
Templates, representing the simplest model
needed to describe a target behavior,
can describe in basic terms this
robot environment interaction, and
generate useful force profiles that can be
anchored to a variety of robot sizes and
morphologies.
We've see the rimless wheel,
the spring-loaded inverted pendulum,
and the lateral leg springing templates
together describe many forms of running
and walking.
These templates have natural energy saving
and stability properties that make them
advantageous behavioral targets for
control.
By anchoring the template dynamics
directly into the mechanism of the body
and legs, stability and control can
be achieved with minimal need for
computation and sensing.
And even when active balance is required,
careful consideration in leveraging
of the underlying template dynamics
proves a powerful tool for robot design.