We had a brief introduction to
parallel composition last segment.
In this segment,
we're going to talk about details.
We'll push on a synthetic
view of parallel composition.
That is as roboticists we want to
construct behaviors using compositions and
we'll talk about how we accomplish that.
And we'll place a special emphasis
on behavioral modularity and
I'll explain what that is.
Jeff talked about
templates in section 2.1.
Just to quickly recap.
Templates are low dimensional
reference dynamics.
In this picture you can see how
we use the idea of templates and
anchors to analyze biological systems.
A complicated system sometimes behaves
like it's actually a simpler one and
the template captures
the underlying simpler dynamics.
This idea is later used to
analyze machines like Rex
as Dan said in section 4.1.
Instead of the bodycentric
view of templates and anchors,
what about a more dynamical systems view?
In this cartoon, the blue line
indicates the template dynamics.
That is they're actually
lower dimensional and
simpler than the full state
space which is in grey.
The actual evolution of the system might
follow something like the red arrows where
the attraction down to the template sub
manifold is called the anchoring dynamics.
Somewhat surprisingly, anchoring is
actually a parallel composition.
Here is my template dynamics,
the blue again and
the anchor dynamics is simply a parallel
composition of something that attracts
down to the template sub manifold.
With them together, you get something
like the picture on the left again.
To summarize, for systems with
a high number of degrees of freedom,
there's really no alternative to
thinking about parallel composition.
Why is this?
It's because uncoordinated degrees
of freedom in a mechanical systems
tend to accumulate energy and
that usually causes the robot to fail.
What happens in lots of animals and
robots is that these extra degrees of
freedom might be passively controlled?
In this situation, they're actually
referred to as something called preflexes.
So either you have preflexes or
you can think about parallel
compositions of templates.
One of the difficulties of
parallel composition is coupling.
To illustrate this, look at this circuit.
There are two physical parts of
the circuit if you look carefully.
An RL circuit over here and
an RC circuit over on the right.
These two separate parts
are connected by the resistor R21.
Let's think about the limit
if R21 goes to infinity.
That would physically
disconnect the circuit and
the current in the RL part would not
interfere with the current in the RC part.
This is a physical decoupling.
And the solutions of the RL part and
the RC part would not interact.
You could say that the evolution of the
system can be represented by this diagonal
linear system or
x1 dot is not affect by x2 and vice versa.
Here's some images of what happens when
you don't have the coupling which are
the arrows in blue and you start slowly
adding coupling by reducing R21
from its initial value of infinity.
You get something like the red lines,
which are slight deformations
of the blue lines.
And if you keep increasing the coupling,
you get higher deformations, but
you can see how it still resembles
the original decoupled system somewhat.
Crosstalk can be much worse
in mechanical systems.
Let's think of a simple system
like a double pendulum.
Which you can think about as a parallel
composition of an upper link and
a lower link, where the controller is just
gravity and there's some natural damping.
So if I held one of the links
of the double pendulum rigid,
you'd imagine that it would
oscillate until it slowly died out.
So the template dynamics is
really a slow oscillation or
fast oscillation where
the energy is not increasing.
That is, if I release
the pendulum from some height,
you would expect it to
not go above that height.
But now let's take a double pendulum.
You can see that even though
I started below the line,
one of the links ended
up crossing the line.
Why is this?
It's really because that the energy in
mechanical systems is coupled tightly,
and energy from one link can
cross over into a second one and
cause obstacles to be hit
where you didn't expect.
And here are the traces, and
you can see that even though,
in the right trace the height
of the system started at zero,
it tends to go above it and
cause failures.
So this kind of mechanical coupling really
messes us up when trying to do parallel
composition in mechanical systems.
To summarize the motivation for parallel
composition, robots have many degrees of
freedom and you either need to
incorporate preflexes at design time or
you need to think about parallel
composition of templates at control time.
Let's talk about this
with a simple example.
Here's a vertical hopper, and what I would
like to do as an engineer is embed this
behavior into my planer hopper, which
is a slightly more complicated system.
So what I'd like to do is to map my
controllers from template to anchor.
So that's part one of the agenda.
However, I would also like to embed
multiple templates, not just one.
For instance, my planar hopper should
not just be able to hop up and down, but
also move laterally on the plane.
To do that, we embed a second template,
the rimless wheel,
which Jeff talking about
in the previous week, and
have both of those controllers
acting on my planar hopper.
Additionally, I would like
the controllers to be decoupled.
I would not like to have to worry
about the fore-aft control, and
the vertical hop control, and vice versa.
However, when anchoring multiple
templates, you have to be worried about
coupling forces, as we saw with the double
pendulum example in the previous slide.
We could either try to cancel these
coupling interactions, which remember get
worse with higher velocities since
Coriolis terms depend on velocity, but
then you would ruin the decouple
nature of our controller.
We'll talk in the next segment
about how it's much preferable
to not have coupling
between our controllers.
Lastly, I've just talked
about the implementation.
But that's not really enough.
You have to be able to verify that
our parallel composition works
both in practice as well as analytically.
Now that I've explained
some of the difficulties,
let see some empirical
parallel compositions.
Raibert was one of the first
to pioneer on this.
Here's a video of a Raibert
hopper hopping up and down.
And this is using the controller that
Jeff described in the previous weeks.
What Raibert did, was he took
this vertical hopping idea, and
added a decoupled controller for
fore aft movement.
And you can see here, hopper is happily
hopping along the boom at control speeds.
It seems like the implementation
was very simple but
there are some considerations
that might not be so obvious.
The ratio of the leg inertia to the body
inertias turns out to be very important to
the decoupled controllers
to work in this example.
For Raibert this ratio was 14:1 for
the body to the leg inertia.
I've made a simulation here where
this ratio is actually changeable.
Here it's hopping fine for a ratio of 7:1.
But then if you keep increasing it so that
it's about 1:1, it doesn't work anymore.
So there's an interesting
interaction of design choices
with the ability to implement
decoupled controllers.
To summarize, in a high degree of freedom
robot, there's no alternative to either
incorporating preflexes or thinking
about parallel composition of templates.
Coupling forces in mechanical systems will
really try to screw us up when we try to
implement decoupled controllers but it's
really preferrable to be able to do this
for a number of reasons, which are going
to be more obvious in the coming lectures.
Lastly verifying that the parallel
composition is correct is difficult, but
it's also very important.
And we're going to talk about
that in the next segment.