In this segment we are going to talk
a little bit about the verification step
that I mentioned at
the end of the last video.
This entails some formalism of
an analysis but as we'll see
in later segment is not critical to the
conceptual ideas of parallel composition.
Let's look at SLIP as
a parallel composition.
Just like Reword did, but
we'll add in some formalism so
that we can really see what's going on.
So the first template in action is
a controlled one degree of freedom,
vertical hopper.
Here's a video of the Pengerboa
which I introduced in week three
doing a vertical hopping.
But it's implemented actually
with the tail wagging up and
down against the passive legs.
This just goes to show you that a pogo
stick need not look like a pogo stick.
What we really care about is
the behavior of the dynamical system.
A vertical hopper can be described in
phase energy coordinates in this way,
where a represents the energy
of the vertical hopper and
this angular coordinate,
psi, represents the phase.
You can see that even if the input,
u, were zero,
the energy would stay conserved, but the
phase would keep going at a rate, omega.
What we choose to do with this system,
is introduce a controller that energizes
in an oscillatory fashion trying to
compensate for the natural dumping.
Here's an example of
an Oscillatory energization.
Here the k term energizes the system and
the a times beta term is really
the natural dumping of the system.
Which, as intuition should point out,
increases as the energy increases.
The analysis of the system is made
simpler by a particular approximation
that's called dynamical averaging.
And without going into
the details too much,
you get something like this very simple
first order linear time in variant ODE.
Which you should be able to solve.
The next template we have to consider is
the Rimless wheel which I have introduced
but now let's think about it as
a model only for forward speed.
The Rimless wheel has more
than one degree of freedom but
here we'll only care about the speed
that which it rolls down the hill
What we'll do with the rimless wheel
is we'll add a lift off torque so
that it's an active rimless wheel and
not just passive.
This is not dissimilar to the Cornell
Ranger pictured here which used lift off
ankle torques to walk a huge distance
with a minimal expenditure of energy.
Let's take a simplistic view of
the dynamics of the rimless wheel.
The continuous dynamics
are pretty well captured
by this equation with suggest that
the energy of the rimless wheel
increases by a fixed amount due to
the rolling every continuous phase.
The impacts,
on the other hand, take away energy where
you can really think about the impacts as
being kind of a coefficient of restitution
effect, as suggested by this equation.
Together, you get this equation for
the return map, where intuitively, some
energy is added and some energy is taken
away to give you a stable forward speed.
What's interesting is that the simplicity
view has a one to one mapping to what
were did templement forward speed
control on his hopping robot.
The mechanism by which that happened
was a stepping controller where
the toe is positioned in flight.
There's no rimless wheel in that
setting but there's really a one to one
correspondence between the rimless
wheel and the stepping example.
In the stepping example there's
a particular stepping angle called
the neutral angle which results
in zero change in speed and
by serving around the neutral angle you
can control your speed effectively.
Together, these two templates
give us a stable hopping behavior
as I've shown you before and
as Rayburn has demonstrated before.
Unfortunately, it turns out that
implementing the parallel composition is
much easier than analyzing it.
This is really the main
part of this section.
So the question is,
does SLIP anchor a vertical hopper?
What does this question mean?
If we go back to full
encoded tap templates and
anchor is what we're asking
is are the dynamics of slip
the same as the vertical hopper in some in
variance sub manifold of it's dynamics.
So how does one go about
proving an anchoring?
This really by demonstrating that there's
a conjugacy of the form just mentioned.
But proving that there isn't a conjugacy,
or there isn't an anchoring is much
more difficult because logically you'd
have to search all possible conjugacies.
However, I will go over the most natural
coordinate change here, and even though it
won't be a proof, hopefully you will see
how this process is quite difficult.
Here the continuous dynamics corresponding
to the extension of the leg in SLIP.
The first term,
corresponds to the spring force.
The second term,
to gravity and the third term,
to the centrifugal force felt by
the mass as it's spins above the toe.
If we define the states base we really
get something like this equation for
the dynamics.
Let's compare to a vertical hopper
where a lot of it is the same but
there are few critical differences.
Firstly, gravity is not meet
projected about the angle data and
there's no centrifugal force.
For this trivial but
kind of obvious change of coordinates,
we see that the dynamics are the same only
if data is zero and data dot is zero.
What these means is that
the leg is really vertical and
hopping vertically and
has no speed at all.
So you can see that it's very challenging
to prove this anchoring because it doesn't
exist for any non-zero forward speed.
Some new research that we're doing is
trying to show that instead of anchoring
the exact dynamics sef.
There's approximation f bar that
has this correspondence and
has all the stability
properties that we require.
To summarize SLIP can actually be
decomposed into a vertical hopper and
a rimless wheel.
A vertical hopper can be
controlled by active damping.
A rimless wheel can be controlled
by active liftoff impulse.
SLIP as a composition works
very well in simulation and
in practice but showing that this
anchoring is exact is almost impossible.
Approximate versions of this
anchoring might be more feasible.