Now it's time to talk about
an empirically instantiated version
of anchoring that's been very
successful in the physical world,
that we still have only part
understanding of, mathematically.
But gives you a good feeling for
what can happen,
when a simple template as Jeff
talked to you about in week three.
Gets anchored in a complicated but
useful body.
In the year 2000-2001 Martin Buehler,
then a professor at McGale University,
designed a new hexapedal machine
together with Uluc Saranli,
then a graduate student at
university of Michigan,
now a professor at Middle Eastern
Techno University in Turkey.
Their machine that they named RHex had
only six motors, one for each hip.
And indeed, that's what they
received their patent for,
a one actuator per hip
compliant legged hexapod.
This underactuation concept had been
pioneered by Buehler in the decade prior.
And he was convinced that it was crucial
to achieve adequate specific power
as we have described before being a very
scarce resource in legged mobility.
He took the single spoke rimless wheel
concept that McGeer has pioneered in 1990,
and he added that to compliance and
single actualization
to come up with a machine that
broke all previous records.
For not simply speed, it clocked
in at one body length per second.
Which was about an order of magnitude
greater than any other machine
that was unplugged had achieved with legs.
It had a reasonable specific resistance,
you'll remember from the first segment.
That specific resistance as
a measure of cost of transport.
This machine not only had an order of
magnitude greater speed, but it was
arguably the first legged machine to run
over highly irregular broken ground.
Here, you see a movie of some of the first
rugged steps that RHex took back in 2001,
and it was very much inspired by the movie
you've seen of the cockroaches
studied by Professor Full at Berkeley.
This badly broken and
complicated landscape
had never before been
traversed by legged machines.
We've discussed the cost of
transport as a measure of
efficiency in the first segment, and here.
I would say that Martin also broke new
ground by showing that the cost of
transport increased over this rugged
terrain, but didn't go through the roof.
And so this machine had
a cost of transport that was
reasonable over level ground, and not at
all unreasonable over badly broken ground.
And so with this specific
resistance of less than ten
as you'll see from the charts
if you go back to segment 1.1.1,
is still actually quite reasonable and
was unusual for its time.
We believe that this is the consequence
of the dynamical design, and
we have good empirical reason,
as I will now discuss.
But as you will see,
the mathematical underpinnings of
these ideas are still underdeveloped.
What can we say about this invention that
had a number of very new properties?
Broke new ground, so
to speak, in legged robotics.
Well, empirically we can say a lot.
Mathematically, we have a little
bit less understanding.
Let's first remember the notion of
anchoring that was brought up in
the previous segment.
Remember that an anchored template is one
which lives in a higher
degree of freedom body,
even though it has only very few
degrees of freedom that count.
This concept was introduced in robotics,
arguably, by Mark Raibert as well,
the guy we've talked about who built
those Ooiginal hopping pogo sticks.
Mark built,
in addition to literal pogo sticks,
he built this mechanism,
that I'm showing in the figure,
which was a quadrupedal version
of his bipedal hopping machine.
He took two of his bipedal machines and
he yoked them together through a body,
and he had a quadruped.
He had two hydraulic degrees of
actuated freedom and one pneumatic
actuator per leg, so each of these legs
had three actuated degrees of freedom.
They were plugged into the wall and
so, there was no power problem.
And what Mark was able to do was
exhibit bounding, pronking, pacing,
trotting gaits.
Unfortunately, we don't have time in this
little module to talk about gaits and
gait space.
But, the gates of animals and the gates
of robots are a wonderful important area.
We'll just ignore it.
We'll just assume that you have
an intuitive idea of what bounding and
pronking, and pacing,
and trotting might be.
Mark was able to exhibit,
on his quadrupedal machine,
all of these combinations of
gaits by very simple manipulation
of the individual hopping pieces,
the hopping legs.
We'll come back to this idea when
we talk about parallel composition
more carefully in the next segment.
For this segment, we'd like to focus
on what it was that these pogo
stick like machines were able to do that
made them so interesting and valuable.
What Mark was able to show was
that by coordinating the legs and
the gait pattern successfully,
he could fool the ground
to thinking that this quadrupedal
machine was really a one-legged,
spring-loaded inverted pendulum.
As we're suggesting in the trace
of the various energies that he
recorded off of his machine.
Now, there had not yet been a off-the-wall
power autonomous machine to even run,
much less to run
in this spring-loaded inverted pendulum
like way, which is what the animals do.
What we found when we were able to
tune RHex properly was that it,
together with it's legs,
when it tuned up properly,
exhibited motions that I'll now
show in the video at slow motion.
I think you can see if you look at this
video carefully in slow motion that
the mass center of the body of
this machine is pitching up and
down, and back and forth much like the
center of mass of a pogo stick would be.
Not only can you see it with your eye,
but we were able to measure
the same sorts of energetic traces
of the spring loaded inverted
pendulum in the mass center
of the body of this machine.
But also, we're able to show that
some of the more detailed states,
some of the leg configurations
that we've talked about in
the kinematics section,
also conformed to the time trajectories
that one would expect to see
in a slip like situation.
And so, what we found was that
properly tuned means the clock had to
be set properly,
I'll talk about the clock very shortly.
And the leg compliances, the springinesses
of the legs, needed to be tuned very,
very carefully.
They're anisotropic, means that
they're very directionally different.
They're stiff in one direction and they're
very compliant in other directions.
These compliances and
the timings of the feet for clock
needed to be tuned up very carefully.
And when they were,
then the RHex empirically could be seen to
anchor this spring loaded inverted
pendulum pogo stick template,
just as the animals do when they run.
We are very excited about that and the
question was, could we understand it and
could we control it?
How would we understand how to tune these
various complicated aspects of the body
of the machine, in order that it could
anchor this very useful running template.
Well, we developed a number of
mathematical approaches to this problem.
The first and most straightforward was
assuming that we could sense every part,
every state of the body, every aspect of
the body and every part of the leg, and
the contact properties of the legs.
We did that in a family of
mathematical models and simulations,
the most important of which and
the simplest of which was a series of
bipedal spring loaded inverted pendulum
templates produced by my then student,
now Professor Uluc Saranli at
Middle Eastern Technical University.
What Uluc did was he took the alternating
tripod gait of this machine,
which I'll now describe and
he virtualized that as a biped.
Alternating tripod is the name of
a gait that hexapedal animals,
insects principally, are almost always
exhibiting when they run at any speed.
Alternating tripod means that the two
left, the two legs in the front and
the rear of one side and the middle leg
of the other side are in phase whilst,
the two legs of the in phase side,
front and
rear, are out of phase and
raised up in the air.
And the other leg on the two legged
down side is up in the air as well.
So it's two sets of three
legs in alternation.
And so these three legs,
two on one side in front and back, and
one on the other side in the middle
are acting as a virtual single leg.
And so they're two virtual single legs and
so this is a virtual biped.
When the animals run they're
running virtually bipedally even
though their support base is larger.
We understood that these
complicated bodies with their
24-degree of freedoms in the legs and
the body combined.
And there are very few number of
actuators would have to be organized
in a very careful way.
There are many many kinematic
singularities in the RHex design.
Particularly when the legs
are all coming down in parallel.
If we focus on this
alternating tripod gait,
which is a ubiquitous bipedal trot in
animals, virtual bipedal trot in animals.
Then, we motivate
a bipedal approximation or
a bipedal projection of the RHex
machine onto this figure that Uluc
drew which was a virtual bipedal
spring-loaded inverted pendulum,
in that each of these two legs was
its own pogo stick to the body and
they would be alternated.
If we introduce the stance control very,
very actively,
where we use the shank springiness,
and the touchdown angle and
the liftoff angle, and we think of
being able to control these things.
Then, we can actually decouple all these
complicated pogo stick dynamics and
achieve a control of this template.
There were other interesting
control features of this actively
anchored mechanism which I
will not trouble you with, but
they were important to
the success of the simulation.
The anchoring control then, was based
upon a quasi-static selection of stands.
Let me explain that in a figure.
Here you see a sagittal plane view of the
RHex, of the physical bodied RHex machine,
wherein there's a virtual
tow sketched in the figure.
That's achieved by tinting the physical
toes in just the right manner so that,
the mass center of the physical body
meets the ground through a virtual line.
That's at the point of a maximum
pressure point of the leg support,
in such a fashion that it feels
to the machine as though there's
really one single virtual leg,
whose angle can now be adjusted.
The touch down angle can now be adjusted
in the virtual leg by adjusting
the cant of the true physical legs.
The limits on the hip torques were very,
very important.
And, we were not able to
maintain stance in the simulation
without violating the very
limited hip torques.
And so we threw away the physical limits
on the torques in order to achieve
the stance phase.
This has to do with the problems of
traction that I described earlier in
the first segment,
when we talked about the cheetah and
it's claws, and how the cheetah
is using its claws to dig in.
If we don't have enough torque, then we
can't dig into the ground with our normal
forces enough to get traction reaction
forces to keep from slipping.
Or from a toe popping off the ground.
When we made all these
physical approximations and
relaxed some of these
physical constraints.
We were able to show
mathematically that this sagittal
plane view of the machine
actually did stabilize
an embedded spring loaded
inverted pendulum.
And we could then take that projection and
use our understanding
of the larger kinematics of
the machine to generalize across
the sagittal plane into the full
six-degree of freedom body.
So that you now see a simulation
of Uluc's anchoring,
actively anchored control of the spring
inverted pendulum in a simulation of
the true physical six-degree of
freedom in the body of RHex machine.