Well, simulations are great.
One of my former students,
now professor Lewis [INAUDIBLE] at
John's Hopkins University was want to
say simulations are doomed to succeed.
[LAUGH] Because we always
throw away a lot of
the physical detail and we needed to throw
away a lot of the physical detail in order
to get these controls which are very
aggressive to work properly.
The chief reason that these controls
couldn't be brought into the physical
world was because
the sensing of the legs and
the contact properties of the legs
turned out to be very, very difficult.
Let's talk about that problem.
Well, why couldn't we bring this
actively controlled machine
into the physical world?
Principally, because we couldn't get, and
probably still are not able
with technology of 2015,
to get good feedback from the legs
up into the body in a manner
which is both accurate enough,
and timely enough to achieve
these very aggressive high
gain feedback control loss.
Before we talk about that in detail, let's
observe that Robert Full, my biologist
collaborator at Berkley, together with
his doctoral student, Devin Jindrich,
who is now at Arizona State University
as a professor in his own right.
Had shown about two years
earlier that the cockroaches,
when they run, are also not able
to use their distal feedback.
It turns out that Bob and
Devin put miniaturized canons on
the backs of cockroaches and they
fire those canons while the cockroaches
are running to impart a huge impulse.
To perturb the gate and it turned out
that the animals recovered their gait so
quickly that it was too quick for
the travel time of a neural
signal from the point of sensing through
the synapse to the point of control.
So the cockroach itself
is stabilizing its body.
First of all, in a mechanical only or
preflexive manner.
No neural signals involved.
The RHex leg contact detection
problem is at least as hard and
harder probably for us than
the cockroach distal feedback problem,
because the RHex legs are free to rotate.
And so, it's very difficult to
get a signal across the gap
between the motor and
the stator of those rotating legs.
My doctoral student, Professor Patron Lin,
now at National Taiwan University,
was able to achieve a actively
fed back leg contact sensor
using a wireless system that was
designed by different doctoral student,
Doctor.
And they were able to get signals but
the signals were quite noisy.
Instead subsequently,
numbers of students have tried to build
virtual leg contact
sensors based upon some
surrogate signal that's picked up when the
leg hits the ground or hits some solid.
Unfortunately, these methods
are either inaccurate or they're slow.
Inaccurate or flawed because we might
use the tracking error when the leg
hits the ground and feels a load and
begins to lose its tracking, as was
explained in the tracking control segment.
The difficulty there is it's very, very
hard to know when your tracking error is
a consequence of the leg touch down or a
consequence of the lagging leg in the air.
Alternatively, Dr.
Aaron Johnson subsequently
was able to build a model of
the recirculating leg and
use that model to detect
residual estimation errors.
And when those estimation
errors went high,
that was a very accurate indication
that the contact had been made.
But unfortunately,
the extra sensing loops introduced
sufficient lag that the stance phase
was over by the time the signal
processing finished and
the contact detection had been made.
So we never ever were
able to get very fast and
very accurate distal feedback from
the legs up into the clock control.
Thus, for many, many, many years,
the control of the RHex gaits has been
a feed forward clock-excited signal
that I will now describe to you.
If you watch this movie, you will see that
there are two virtual hands on this clock.
One hand is moving quickly, and
the other hand is moving slowly.
And then when that fast hand comes down
to the bottom, it changes speed and
it moves slowly whilst the other
hand moves around quickly.
These hands are virtual
spokes of a virtual wheel.
In fact, they're two virtual
out of phase wheels and
when one spoke is on the ground,
the other spoke of the virtual wheel
on the other side is rotating quickly
to come down to touchdown just in time for
the other leg to lift off.
This is the clock that we've
always called the Buehler Clock
in honor of Martin Buehler,
who first devised it.
This is the feed forward clock excitation
signal that I have been discussing so far.
What can we say about
a clock excited hopper?
Well Dr. Komsuoglu,
whose name I mentioned to you before,
succeeded in showing that a clock
excited vertical hopper could
indeed be stabilized successfully
by a properly tuned clock.
And this analytical result meant
that the tuning of the clock and
the tuning of the compliance could be
done mathematically at design time.
What happens when we increase
the degrees of freedom?
Let's go from a simple one degree of
freedom vertical hopper to something like
a clock excited two degree of freedom
spring-loaded inverted pendulum.
Here if the clock
has the effect forcing the leg to touch
down at the same angle each time.
Then, we were able to do an analysis
with my colleague and collaborator,
Professor Phil Holmes at Princeton and
his graduate student, Rafael Ghigliazza.
And we were able to come up with good
sufficient and necessary conditions for
stabilizing this slip template
in this clocked hopper.
Unfortunately, when we moved to
the next degree of freedom when we
added a body attitude and tried to account
for the three degree of freedom clocked
spring loaded and
inverted pendulum with attitude.
We were only be able to get very loose,
sufficient and very,
very loose necessary conditions for
stability.
And so
to this day the control of the anchoring
of the pogo stick, or
the spring loaded inverted pendulum,
in the physical RHex is
an unfinished bit of analysis.
And to this day, we're missing
complete clock anchoring conditions so
that we don't know how to tune
the machine properly at design time and
we're forced to tune the machine
empirically at run time.
Let's describe that process.
Tuning Task Open Loop Gaits is not so
hard if you take
the vantage point of
a simple learning mechanism.
So, we will fallback on an empirical
tuning method which is a very,
very simple form of learning.
Which uses a gradient descent in
the parameter space of the clock to
try to improve a cost function that robot
measures again, and again, and again.
The natural cost function to use
is the specific resistance, and
the robot can measure its own specific
resistance instantaneously if you take
the power divided by speed
version of specific resistance.
Go back to the first segment
1.1.1 if you forgotten about what
we meant by specific resistance.
If we use specific resistance or
a modified version
thereof as the cost function,
we can measure our time and
measure the battery power used to
achieve a traversal of a known distance.
And by measuring the time against the
distance and using the power consumed for
that leg, we achieve an estimate of
the specific resistance for that gait.
And so what this robot would do,
it would autonomously run ten meters.
Turn itself around by
watching the end stop.
Start its clock,
run again with a different gait.
Come to the end,
evaluate a specific resistance.
Turn around, choose a different
set of gait parameters that would
lower where it predicted would
lower the cost in the next gait and
repeat again, and again, and again.
Let me give you some feeling for
what this is like empirically.
So here is an early trial
where the robot was
running at about 40
centimeters per second.
And as it tuned itself around,
you can see the gait parameters changing
in the slides, and you can see from the
movie that the gaits begin to be faster,
and faster yet
without much energetic cost.
Until finally, we achieved empirically
gaits that looked like this.
Here's an example of
a reasonably fast RHex gait.
This is RHex running across mixed
terrain at five body lengths per second,
unheard of for a machine at that point,
legged machine at that point.
And this was result of this very, very,
very simple learning method whose
descent its specific resistance as
a function of iteration is depicted in
the graph next to this running movie.
This is much as we understand about RHex.
Analytically, we're constantly interested
in improving our understanding
mathematically, and we're constantly
attempting to achieve better feedback,
more accurate feedback, and
faster feedback from the legs to the body.
And in large measure, this has motivated
some recent developments in the lab
that we'll be discussing in the next
two segments bearing on parallel
composition of a much more aggressive and
analytically successful and
empirically successful kind.
Stay tuned.