In this section, we're going to
review the study of kinematics,
which is related to the motion of bodies.
This is distinct from dynamics,
because we don't consider the forces that
cause the accelerations of these bodies.
First, we define the phrase
degrees of freedom.
These are the number of parameters that
fully define the system in its space.
A rigid body and
ambient space has six degrees of freedom.
Typically, they are x, y, and z,
which are three positions, and roll,
pitch, and yaw, which are three angles.
In this figure,
we see a plane who's degrees of freedom
have been highlighted in
the typical convention.
In robotics, we're interested in
both active degrees of freedom,
which are explicitly controlled by
actuators, as well as the passive degrees
of freedom that are governed
by the system's dynamics.
Most robots are highly underactuated.
This means that the majority of
the degrees of freedom are passive and
not controlled by the system's actuators.
In this video, we see the pendulum robot.
The body of the robot has
only two degrees of freedom,
as it is constrained on a boom.
The leg also has two degrees of freedom.
One of which, the rotation, is active
as it is controlled by the motor.
The other is the extension of the leg,
which is simply governed
by the attached spring.
Joints are an example of
a holonomic constraint and
reduce the number of degrees
of freedom of a system.
In this video,
we see a leg from the minitaur robot
demonstrating multiple revolute joints.
In this video, we see a similar
leg jumping on a linear rail.
All of the pin joints
in the minitaur leg and
the linear rail constrain the attached
links to only one degree of freedom.
Another example of a joint that has
one degree of freedom is a screw
even though the translation and
rotation are coupled.
An example of a two degree of
freedom joint in the plane
is an idealized wheel spinning on ice.
The rotation and
translation are completely decoupled.
Kutzbach's equation determines the number
of degrees of freedom in a planar system.
M is the number of degrees of freedom,
N is the number of links in the system,
J1 is the number of one-degree
of freedom joints, and
J2 is the number of
two-degree of freedom joints.
Once solved, if M is equal to zero,
the system is fully constrained and
can't move.
Another class of constraints
are called non-holonomic,
meaning they cannot be described
using the position of the system.
These constraints that are not only
a function of position can, for
example, be a function of velocity.
In this video, we see that the car wants
to move sideways into the parking spot.
However, there's a non-holonomic
constraint preventing
any lateral velocity.
The car can however translate in that
direction using a parallel parking
manuever.
We are now interested in establishing
a relationship between the position of
the robots end effector,
X, in its free space, and
all of the machines joint angles, theta.
The forward kinematics are when
the joint angles are known and
the position of the end
effector is to be determined.
Typically, in robot arms, the joint angles
are known as they are instrumented, and
so it is of interest to figure out
where the end effector will be
given a set of joint angles.
Inverse kinematics pose the opposite
problem where the position
of the end effector is known and
a joint angles are to be computed.
In this video,
we see a robot arm doing a welding task.
The end effector needs to follow a desired
trajectory in ambiance space and so
inverse kinematics must be use
back out the joint angles.
These joint angles are then passed to the
machine as desired angles for the motor.
Here we see a much simpler
revolute-revolute robot arm.
The angle between the first link and
the base is theta one and
the angle between the first link and
the second link is theta two.
It's important to note that
theta two is a relative angle.
Since the position of the end effector,
X, is a function, F,
of the joint angles, theta, calculating
F represents the forward kinematics.
Some dimensions have been broken out in
this image to help solve the problem of
forward kinematics.
Using the same revolute-revolute arm,
if the end effector position is known,
inverse kinematics can let us solve for
the joint angles.
Since the forward kinematics are known,
this represents a system
of non-linear equations.
The inverse kinematics can be
found from the forward kinematics
by solving a system of equations.
Generally, this system of
equations is non-linear and
can be solved with
trigonometric identities.
Simpler cases can be solved in MATLAB by
making the desired variables symbolic and
using the solve function.
Solving the inverse kinematics
amounts to inverting
the system of equations
represented by the function F.
All the previous linkages that
we've considered are serial
in that there's only one chain between
the ground and the end effector.
Parallel mechanisms have multiple chains
connecting the end effector to the ground.
Solving the kinematics of parallel
mechanism is much more difficult than for
serial mechanisms.
Here we will go over a concrete
example using the minitaur leg.
In this figure we see the minitaur leg
with the motor angles theta one and
theta two Illustrated.
We would like to solve
the forward kinematics and
so get a solution for X and Y as
a function of theta one and theta two.
This task greatly simplified if we
use a couple of coordinate changes.
The first coordinate change that will
be helpful is to go from theta one and
theta two to alpha and beta,
the mean and different coordinates.
Once alpha and beta are computed,
a further coordinate change to polar
coordinates help solve the problem.
We now consider the infinitesimal
kinematics for these linkages.
This is done by computing the matrix
of partial derivatives of the system
known as the Jacobian.
Here we see the Jacobian,
J, computed where the rows represent
the system of equations and
the columns represent the partial
derivatives of the different joint angles.
By multiplying the Jacobian by
DT over DT and rearranging,
we see that the Jacobian describes the
relationship between joint velocities and
velocities at the end effector.
Thanks to the principle of virtual
work the Jacobian transpose
can be used to relate the forces at the
end effector to the torques at the joints.
This Jacobian transpose inverse represents
the effective mechanical advantage for
the system.
It scales the torques at the joint
into forces at the end effector.