Now we are going to take the ideas from
the previous segment that are familiar
to you from your correspond
ordinary differential equations and
your course on linear algebra,
and we're going to
delve into territory that possibly
you've never seen before.
There will be some exercises for
you to work through,
to try to fix the ideas in your thinking.
But likely, we're reaching the point
here where you will need to take more
advance courses in the future and in order
to make complete sense of these ideas.
Our notion of including this
material in this special MOOC
course is that you would see how
the mathematical ideas fit and
are needed to understand the more
complicated aspects of the robot
behaviors that we'll be
discussing in future segments.
In this segment,
I'll be talking about just a pendulum,
a simple pendulum hanging in
the gravitational field and
we will be pretending that
this pendulum is the leg.
A one degree of freedom leg,
a swinging leg with one joint of a body.
If you'd prefer to think of it as an arm,
that's fine, but
we'd like to think about it
as the simplest appendage.
As you know in most animals and
in most robots that are interesting,
there will be many,
many, many more joints.
Often, they'll be revolute joints.
And so you can begin to think about
compound pendula when you start thinking
of the many jointed robot arms and
robot legs that we'll be discussing.
These many jointed pendula have far more
complicated behaviors than the simple
one degree of freedom pendulum
that I'll be discussing, but
the idea and the mathematical connections
are very, very much the same.
And we will try to get that idea
across by making the connection
between this non linear one degree
of freedom pendulum motion,
which perhaps you've not seen before.
In contrast to the one degree of
freedom linear mass on a spring
from the previous segment that you've
seen before in physics and ODE theory.
The first new idea that we'll
be discussing at great length
in a future segment on kinematics
is the relative motion
between constrained rigid
bodies creates the normality,
because the pendulum swings around and
around and around.
The mass comes back to the same
place that it's been, which would
never be possible in the straight
line motion of the original protocol.
This periodic phenomenon is characteristic
of all the interesting kinematics,
revolute joints are much more useful
in general than prismatic joints as
you'll come to see in
our kinematic section.
Yet, they account for
the origin of the normality.
So let's look at the picture of
the simple pendulum with point mass, m at
some position p and I'd like you to think
about p as having a spacial component.
There's a position on the plane
in the horizontal direction x and
a position on the plane in
a vertical direction z and
there's this fixed distance l,
which the masses constrained
to travel on there by forming a circular
arc, whenever it travels at all.
It can travel along that circular arc for
many, many,
many degrees depending on
how much energy it has.
So our variable p,
which looks like a planer variable,
because it has two components, px and
pz is really a one degree
of freedom variable, but
a nonlinear freedom variable wstablished
by the kinematics of the simple pendulum.
We'll model the geometric
relation using polar coordinates,
which you'll remember from
high school probably.
Namely, we'd like to think
about the horizontal and
the vertical components
of this point mass, p
as having a radial component l, which is
fixed and an angular component theta.
So that using trigonometry,
we can express the position p, px and
pz as the function g
of the variable theta.
Theta is a scalar variable, g is a vector.
So g takes the scalar variable, theta,
the angle of the pendulum and
gives us back,
reads out for us,
the Cartesian positions, px and
pz of the mass that's constrained
to ride on that pendulum.
G is a special function and
its called the kinematic function or
the forward kinematics and
we think about it as mapping,
the joint space that is
the space of shaft angles into
the workspace,
that is the space of positions.
When we introduce the kinematics ideas
later on in this MOOC, we will talk about
kinematics at great length, but
we will be increasingly less mathematical,
because the mathematics becomes very,
very much more complicated.
Here in this segment, we're still
going to talk about the concepts in
the mathematics in a unified manner.
Hoping that it will give you some
insight later on when you study these
more complicated kinematics
in greater depth.
So we will now having discussed
the kinematics of the pendulum,
we will now introduce the dynamics of the
pendulum by introducing a potential force.
The potential force that we're
interested in, of course is gravity.
Gravity in the Cartesian world
looks like a constant accelerator.
So gravity adds 9.8 meters per
second squared acceleration and
you can see that we now have a new
differential equation in theta.
It looks a little bit like the high
double dot equation that we had before in
the previous segment on linear time and
variant,
one degree of freedom particle dynamics.
But now we've got
the nonlinear term sine theta,
which is a consequence of the nonlinearity
introduced through the kinematics
Well, we could agonize about
solving this differential equation.
We've given the dynamics and
l squared theta double dot
equals this right-hand side
function sine theta, but
we'll find that the mathematicians
have discovered a while
ago that these nonlinear systems
cannot be solved in closed form.
The way the Linear Systems
can be solved in closed form.
Fortunately, the energy dynamical
systems point of view that we took in
the previous slide, where we thought
about the energy in a norm like fashion,
those ideas do generalize, and
we'll proceed to use those ideas here.
Well, how can we repeat the analysis of
the linear case in this nominal setting?
Let's remember what we did.
We realized that there was a Kai,
Kai dot plane.
Here, we're going to realize that
there is a theta, theta dot plain.
Namely, what we will do is we will
assign to q one, the variable theta.
And we will assign to q two
the variable theta, theta dot.
Please keep in mind that q,
the phase variable.
Is two dimensional for a very,
very different reason that p.
P is the partition position
of the point mass.
Really, this point mass is constraint to
have just one degree of freedom, theta.
So, we are looking now with the variable
q, at the phase space of theta,
namely q has coordinance, position and
velocity even thought
unlike the old vector x
in the previous segment,
the vector q lives in a non linear space.
We can write down a first order
depherntial equation in q the same way
we wrote down the first order depherntial
equation in x in the previous section.
Namely q one dot d by d
t of theta is theta dot
which is just the second derivative and
second position q2.
In q2 dot we realize q2
dot is d by dt of q1.
So, d by dt of b by dt of q one,
is q one double dot, and
q one double dot means that we should
solve for theta double dot in this
scalar second order physical
version of this first order,
two-dimensional system
that we're writing down.
The mathematician's understand enough
about equation five that they can promise
us that every initial condition still has
a good projectory that I'm denoting q of
t through the initial condition q0.
But unlike the original
equation of the linear time and
varying case,
qt is not available in closed form.
Let's push on.
Instead, let's try to use
an energy conservation argument to
reduce the properties of q(t) over time.
Let me write down again
the total energy of the simple pendulum.
Now, I'm going to write down the kinetic
energy of the pendulum which depends only
on the velocity q2.
Together with the potential energy
due to gravity which depends only
on the angle position q1.
I once again must do
the power calculation.
That I tried to do an succeeded
in the linear case.
Namely, I would like to show
that with no dissipation at
all Hamilton was correct and
the total energy is conserved.
Let's do that computation.
Let's show that D by DT of Ata.
When Ata is composed along
the motions of this system,
that d by d t of Ata is always zero,
so that ata is constant.
I'm going to write down in theta and
theta dot coordinates, and
then rewrite them in q1 q2
coordinates to get the expression
for Ata as a function of q at any time, t.
I'm going to realize that
because of conservation
it's true and
I can rewrite q either q1 or q2,
let's say we'll write q2
as a function of q1 and
now, I'm plotting on the q1 q2 plane-
In red the function Q2
of Q1 that we get by
assuming that the total
energy is conserved
If we add damping it will turn
out that there's a viscous churn.
And our d by dt computation of
total energy will reveal what
Lord Kelvin realized,
which is that the total energy
is no longer conserved, but
must be decaying down to zero.
These computations are not hard to do,
but they will take some time, and
we provide exercises for
you to work on them if you care to In
a supplementary material to this lecture.
Let's now pass on, assuming that
these derivations are correct,
and interpret the change of energy,
the negative change of energy
as a basin like property.
Namely, we're going to look at
two different trajectories.
We're going to look at the trajectory
around the fixed point
at the bottom and
the fixed point at the top.
What do I mean by a fixed point?
I mean, what you know physically that if
you position the pendulum in the earths
gravitational field with no velocity,
with the pendulum pointing straight down,
it will stay there forever.
Similarly, if you position the pendulum
straight up with no velocity and
you balance it exactly right intuitively
that it will also stay there forever.
But you also intuitively know that
these two different fixed points or
fixed positions of the pendula have
very very very different behaviors.
If you position the pendulum underneath
down under, it will stay there forever and
if you bump it It will at least
oscillate and if there's damping,
it will oscillate back down to
the 0,0 no energy position.
In contrast,
if you start with the pendulum
pointed exactly up at the fixed point.
And you bump it a little bit.
Whether or not there's damping.
This pendulum will escape
from its top position, and
it will continue to oscillate
forever if there's no damping or
it will die down to the bottom
under fixed point asymptotically.
In either case,
the top behavior is unstable,
the bottom behavior is stable and
we must now develop a mathematical
way of thinking about it and
analyzing and talking about
such different circumstances.
Let's look at the behavior down under,
a stable fixed point.
The equilibrium motion or the fixed
point motion is constant over time.
Namely, if I start at theta equals
zero and theta dot equals zero,
I'll stay there forever.
The pendulum at the top with
theta is equal to pi, and
theta dot is equal to zero, is also a
fixed point, but will show it's unstable.
First, let's define what
we mean by stability.
Stability is the notion that
motions that start close together
should stay close together.
Asymptotic stability, which is even
more important to us, adds the notion
that motions that start close together,
not only stay close together, but
actually come asymptotically closer and
closer until they converge.
You know intuitively
that this is just whats going to
happen to the damped pendulum.
You know that if you knock it a little
bit off it's bottom fixed point, that
it'll oscillate a little bit, and settle
down to the zero, zero, zero energy state.
We would like to use energy methods to
show that this is true mathematically.
Let's look at the pendulum
near the bottom, and
we'll see that its total energy
gives us a norm-like shape curve.
There close circles close to the bottom
when we express total energy level curves,
and since the power is non positive,
we know that we're going to get a red,
yellow,
blue picture in the non-use setting,
just like what we got in the linear case.
In the linear case, these red curves
were analytically determined.
In this case, these red curves
are developed by numerical simulation,
and they're not closed form,
but mathematically we
know that they must be converging for the
exact same arguments that we used before.
We conclude that the bottom fixed
point has asymptotic stability,
and we've never needed to solve for
the motions, because we showed that
the total energy is decreasing.
That idea is summarized in this
total energy basin picture,
where you see the red motions in
the face plain, Q1, Q2 face plain below.
And projected up onto the energy
surface as blue ghost curves
showing that all the energy
is being sucked out
of any of these initial conditions by
the viscous damping of the pendulum shaft.
In contrast, let's go to the unstable
fixed point at the top, and
do the same computation.
The power is still nonpositive.
D by D T of ata is still negative, so
the power is still nonpositive, and
so the energy must be decreasing.
But let's see what that means.
If we plot the level curves of
the total energy function near the top,
where theta dot is equal to 0 but
theta is equal to pi, then we see that
our level curves are saddle like.
And indeed when we plot numerically in
red, the solution trajectories over time,
we see that energy indeed is decreasing,
but
it's decreasing by running down in
one direction, and then running
down further in the other direction
till we get bluer, and bluer, and bluer.
So energy dissipation in this
case does not apply convergence.
Around the unstable fixed point,
the total energy is not norm-like, and
therefore its decay does not tell
us anything about stability, and
in fact enables us to deduce instability.
We conclude that it's lonely at the top,
it's unstable at the top.
And we show this again by thinking about
the total energy surface as a saddle
in space, where the red motions
over time are being projected
into these blue ghost curves on the energy
surface, and we can see that running
down the saddle doesn't mean that your
going to run to the point of the saddle.
It means that your going to run near
the point and run off the saddle,
all the way down to
the stable fixed point below.
We can do this without ever
computing the solutions.
I find it convenient to illustrate what's
going on with these red numerically
computed trajectories, but the blue story
is all you need mathematically to conclude
that this fixed point is unstable,
and the fixed point below is stable.
The total energy basin defines a task.
We're going to think about
these energy basins as
task symbols, and we're going to try
to start composing these task symbols
later on in this series of lectures.
The Basin properties were established
rigorously only in the late 20th Century.
These are greedy, tireless efforts
of the physical system to get
to the bottom of the local fixed point,
and we're going to try always to
encode what we want out of our
robots in these very robust terms,
because we don't need to know that
much about the initial conditions.
We don't need to know that much
about the details of the friction.
All we need to know is
that the friction or
whatever energetic method is pulling the
energy away from the fixed points we don't
like toward the fixed
points that we do like.
Best yet, these properties are persistent,
in that we don't need to know exactly what
the masses are or
exactly what the spring constants are.
These properties will still
persist under in the parameters.
So the notion of dynamical task encoding,
ideas that I began to think about 20 or
30 years ago, have lasted, and
generalized, and
enable us to begin to implement more and
more complicated behavior using artificial
potential energy landscape functions.
These ideas we're going to try and
convey to you more intuitively
as the segments go along.
But we included this more mathematical
rendition in the simple one degree of
freedom case, so that you could if you
wanted to make the connection between
the intuitive ideas that we're presenting
later, and the mathematics that underpins
them, and introduce those ideas
to your future study goals.