Those of you who have taken
multivariable calculus will remember
the Multivariable Taylor Series.
What is a Taylor Series?
Well my immutable colleague
professor Rob Griest,
who has the world's best calculus MOOC,
teaches us that we should think about
nice functions as being very, very, very
long polynomials, meaning that you can
expand nice functions by Taylor Series
into higher and higher and
higher degree polynomials, and get better
and better and better approximations.
This is called Taylor's Theorem.
And the notion of nice's captured
formally by the word analytic.
Go take Rob’s course if you’re
interested in what this means.
From our point of view what
it means is that we can
expand a functions f of x at any point x.
In the neighborhood of some
interesting .x* using the value
of function adec * plus
a linear approximation,
achieved by taking the derivative
of the function of x*, and
multiplying the difference from that
x star point by that derivative, and
then forgetting about a bunch of remainder
terms called the Taylor Remainder,
which are guaranteed to get very,
very small very quickly.
We'll think about this second
term as the linearization
of the nonlinear function f(x).
And let me remind you that
capital F at x* is the Jacobean.
It's the matrix of partial derivatives
evaluated at that point of interest.
The linearisation of F at x* turns
out to be extremely important and
valuable in the world
of dynamical systems.
If you recall the first segment,
we showed that a linear dynamical
system could be completely solved.
Whereas, in general, nonlinear
dynamical systems are unsolvable.
However, there's the hope that
the linearized dynamics of a non
linear system might actually
closely describe the properties
of that non linear system at least in
the neighborhood of a distinguished point.
We'll illustrate this again using
our damped pendulum back from
the previous sections, so
I'm plotting for you in equation 6.
I'm writing down for you, again,
a reminder of what the right hand side of
the differential equation looked like.
F sub sp the function, the field vector or
the vector field, as it's called, of the
simple pendulum on the right hand side.
At the bottom point,
at the bottom equilibrium state,
let's evaluate the Jacobean,
the matrix of partial derivatives,
of little f, sub sp, at q*, q* being 0,0.
And let's plug that q* into
the Jacobean matrix, capital F.
And let's evaluate it, and that's exactly
what we've done in this bottom row.
That's the linearized dynamics
of this nom in your system,
the pendulum, at its bottom fixed point.
At the top, we have the same formula for
the Jacobean, but
notice that we're plugging in the top
fixed point, which is the angle at theta,
180 degrees above ground, above the
downward pointing part, and at 0 velocity.
And when we plug that value of theta in,
of course, we get a rather different
matrix, the same Jacobean matrix,
the same linearization function,
but it's being evaluated
at two very different q*'s.
First we did it at the bottom, and
the second we did it at the top.
We're going to introduce changes
of coordinates to talk about
the normal forms of
these dynamical systems.
First, in general,
that is away from fixed points.
And then in particular,
close to fixed points.
A change of coordinates is a one to
one in smooth continuous function.
That is continuous partial derivatives,
continuous Jacobean matrix.
If it's inverse function is also smooth,
then we'll call a change of coordinates.
And what we would like to do is,
we would like to write the old
dynamics in the new coordinates.
To do so,
if we're given a differential equation,
x dot = f(x), and
a change of coordinate, y = h(x),
where h is one of these
continuously invertible and
continuous smooth functions.
Then we'll take D by Dt of y, and
we'll use the chain rule to
get our hands on D by Dt of x.
Let's do that.
We'll see that y dot is in the chain rule.
Is the Jacobean of h
times times d by dt of x.
But x d by dt solves
the differential equation.
And so that reduces to the Jacobean
of h times the vector field f.
But we can substitute for
x in that equation by using h inverse.
And so suddenly we have a new differential
equation, y dot equals f tilde of y,
where f tilde of y is said
to be conjugate to f.
It's not the same form as f.
F tilde is very, very different.
It looks very,
very different when you write it down.
But it has the same properties and
the same behaviors.
In exactly analogous way to
the diagonalized matrix capturing
the linear properties in normal
coordinates of the matrix,
whose eigenvectors you
found to diagonalize it.
The normal form of any vector
field away from a fixed point
is always a constant vector field, simple.
It's not to say that the original vector
field had this simple behavior, but
it's conjugate to it, and
so a change of coordinates will
make it look simple in that way.
We're interested in the normal
form at fixed points as well.
So what we mean by the normal form is
reducing by change of coordinates,
a function to it's simplest
polynomial conjugate.
The Flowbox Theorem,
to summarize this idea, says that
if you are away from the fixed point, then
your dynamics is conjugate automatically.
At least in the small neighborhood
of any non-fixed point.
Your dynamics is conjugate to
a boring old constant flow dynamics.
The normal form near a fixed
point is much more interesting.
The Taylor Remainder never is going to
be of interest to us in this discussion,
but the constant term at a fixed
point by definition, vanishes.
We suppose that x* is a fixed point, and
what that means is that f vanishes
at x* as depicted in this equation.
Now, our leading term is the linear
vector field, capital F evaluated x*.
Where remember capital F is
the matrix of partial derivatives of
the original non-linear field
evaluated at the fixed point x*.
It dominates.
And it turns out not only does it
dominate, but there's a theorem
the Hartman Grobman Theorem,
which I am going to abbreviate HA, and
I'm going to call it
the Hyperbolic Approximation Theorem.
You have to look at more complicated
books to really understand this theorem.
But what we should understand is that in
the neighborhood of a nice fixed point,
the non-linear dynamics is
conjugate to its linearization.
Not only is the linearized dynamics
dominating but it actually completely
captures the behavior so long as x*
has the property of being hyperbolic
which is a fancy way of saying it
has no purely imaginary eigenvalues.
Again, this is a very long story that
I'm just giving a small mention of,
and I'm referring you to the legendary
textbook by Professor John Guckenheimer
and Phil Holmes, that is still
considered to be the Bible of
nonlinear dynamical systems, if you become
interested in following these ideas.
The fixed point at the bottom, now,
we're being told by this theorem,
should be captured, behaviorally,
by the linearized dynamics at the bottom.
Well, the linearized dynamics is
governed in turn by the eigenvalues,
the roots of the characteristic
polynomial of that matrix,
that we just calculated
in the previous slide.
Let's compute the eigenvalues.
And we see that the eigenvalues actually
are negative, have negative real part.
The have nonzero real part assuming
assuming we have positive damping.
The behavior near
a hyperbolic fix point then,
including the stability behavior,
is governed by the linearized dynamics.
And so the change of coordinates
preserves the stability properties.
Continuous, continuously changeable change
of coordinates takes bounded sets, so
it preserves stability.
It's continuous, and
so it preserves limits,
so we preserve asymptotic stability.
And so the stability properties
have to be the same, and so
the lineraization governs the stability
properties of the hyperbolic fixed points.
Taylor says linearization dominates,
hyperbolic approximation
guarantees that linearization
actually determines stability.
So that the damped pendulum
near the fixed point
can be understood behaviorally by
looking at it's linearization.
And here I depict that
by juxtaposing the red
nominare flow against the linearized
dynamics of the flow near the fixed
points for different parametric values of
the pendulum down at it's fixed point.
Again, we have some exercises where you
can do some of these calculations, and
do some of your own exploring,
but we'll press on.
In contrast, near and
very near the top fixed point,
we once again see that the nonlinear
dynamics is closely approximated
by linear saddles, and
the linear saddles are clearly unstable.