This lecture provides a very brief
introduction to the dynamics and
control of robots.
Dynamics deals with the motions of
systems acted upon by forces and torques.
This is an important area of study for
roboticists because robots move by
creating forces and
torques on their environment.
So a robot's dynamics explains what forces
and torques are needed to generate motion.
Even when we know the dynamics
choosing the right forces and
torques to control a robot
can be a very tricky problem.
And as part of a whole
field in engineering and
mathematics called control theory.
Today we are going to go
over a very useful tool
used by engineers to explicitly write
out the dynamics as some simple systems.
And then go over a popular method
of controlling those systems.
Just a word of warning, the math in this
lecture is a little more involved than in
many of the previous lectures.
But our intention in doing this is to
give you practical engineering tools
that you can use to
apply to real problems.
You likely learned about Newton's Laws
in your introductory physics course.
They tell us that mechanical systems obey
second order differential equations.
You need differential equations
where there are no more than
two derivatives in it of any variable.
Newton's Laws let us model
the accelerations of robots,
as function of their speed,
velocity, and external forces.
In the kinematics section of this course,
you learn how to generate the equations
and motion for
a system using Free Body Diagrams.
Free Body Diagrams work
well in simple systems.
But often times robotic models
use complicated geometry and
coordinate systems.
It can make free body diagrams cumbersome.
In these cases,
writing out the components of the internal
forces can be tedious especially when
using rotating coordinate systems which is
pretty common when modeling robot joints.
Oftentimes, writing out the energy of such
systems is much simpler than writing out
all the forces.
It turns out that there's another way of
generating the equations of motions for
a system from the mechanical energy alone.
So you don't need to
write out all the forces.
This formulation is known
as Lagrangian Mechanics and
is another equivalent way of
expressing Newton's laws.
For systems that aren't acted
upon by outside forces,
Lagrangian Mechanics says
that the equations of motion
are given by taking the kinetic energy,
subtracting potential energy.
And then applying a special expression
called the Euler-Lagrange operator and
setting the result to 0.
One big advantage of Lagrangian Mechanics
is that since this process is so simple,
it is easy to automate in software once
you can write down the system's energy.
Let's go over this in more detail
before we do a simple example.
The mechanical energy of a system
is the sum of its kinetic energy,
the energy from its motion,
and potential energy.
For example the energy due to gravity or
springs.
Even in complicated systems,
the kinetic and
potential energies are often much
easier to write out than the force is.
The difference between the kinetic and
the potential energy has a name, and
it's called a Lagrangian.
By applying the Euler-Lagrange
operator to the Lagrangian and
setting the results to 0,
you get the equations of motion.
The Euler-Lagrange operator simply takes
the partial derivative of velocities,
differentiates that with respect to time,
and
subtracts away the partial
derivative of positions.
The form of the Euler-Lagrange operator
and the reason all of this works is
a consequence of the principle in physics
called the principle of least action.
We don't have time to go into
details of it today, but
feel free to look it up
online if you're interested.
Finally, all of this accounts for
internal forces, but
if external forces
are acting on the system,
all you need to do is replace these
forces with the zero at the end.
As a quick example of how to
use Lagrangian mechanics,
let's derive the equations of motion for
a simple pendulum.
A simple pendulum consists of a mass
m attached to a rod of length l
that is free to rotate around
some stationary pivot point.
Gravity pulls the mass downwards.
Let's say that when the rod is vertically
downwards it has an angle of zero radians.
So the state of the system is given by the
rod angle and the rod angular velocity.
The first step is to write out the kinetic
and potential energy for the system.
The kinetic energy is given
by 1/2 the moment of inertia
times the angular velocity squared.
Which simplifies to one half the mass
times the rod length squared
times the angular velocity squared.
The potential energy is simply
the energy due to gravity.
Which is equal to the negative
of the mass times the rod length
times the acceleration due to gravity,
time the cosine of the rod angle.
The Lagrangian is then the difference
between the Kinetic and
the Potential energy.
Let's apply the Euler-Lagrange
operator to the system term by term.
The partial derivative at the Lagrangian
with respect to position is equal to mgl
sine theta.
Now in this case we get a scalar, but
if the system had multiple degrees of
freedom we would instead get a vector
whenever we take a partial derivative.
The partial derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to velocity is equal to ml
squared times the angular velocity.
And differentiating with
respect to time gives
ml squared times the angular acceleration.
We get the equations of motion when
we combine these two terms and
set the results to 0.
Notably, when we simplify the equations,
we see that the mass cancels out,
leading to the interesting result
that if the frequency of a simple
pendulum is unaffected by its mass.
The equations of motion for a system
resulting from the Euler-Lagrange operator
have a nice structure that
can be useful to understand.
To demonstrate this structure, we've gone
ahead and derived the equations of motion
for the spring loaded inverted pendulum,
or slip template.
By rearranging terms, we can put
the equations into a generalized
f = ma form where the accelerations
are being multiplied by an inertial
matrix containing the mass terms.
And all of this equals the sum
of the generalized forces.
These forces include the Coriolis and
centrifugal forces
caused by rotating reference frames
represented by the matrix C.
And the forces from potential fields
such as gravity are represented by
the vector N.
External forces represented by the vector
tau are added to the right side of
the equation as well.
This representation of the general
dynamics, regardless of the geometry or
coordinate system,
shows that forces always need to act
through the mass to accelerate the system.
Thus, as robots get heavier, they lose
the ability to accelerate as quickly.
Putting big heavy actuators on
a robot isn't always a good idea
if those actuators can't generate a lot
of torque or force for their weight.
Sometimes a light motor that
can produce a lot of torque for
its weight can accelerate a robot
more than a heavy one that
produces more torque but
less for its weight.
So, this concludes our discussion of
using Lagrangian mechanics to write out
the dynamics when modeling a robot.
Now that we know how to write
out the dynamics for a robot
telling us how forces and twerks generated
by the actuators cause the system to move.
What do we do with it?
Well, we would like our robot to
choose a right actuator commands, so
it executes some kind of desired behavior.
Often this takes the form of
going to a certain state.
For example,
setting some desired joint angles or
moving forward at say
one meter per second.
Today we'll focus on these sort
of behaviors where a robotic
task can be encoded as reaching
some desired position or velocity.
This idea of using the inputs to a system,
which in our case are motor commands,
to achieve some desired behavior is
ubiquitous enough in engineering and
mathematics, that it is itself
a field called control theory.
We do not have time today to do any
justice to a proper introduction into
control theory, but we're going to briefly
introduce two techniques that have
relevance to getting robots to
achieve some desired states.
These techniques are called
Inverse Dynamics Control and
Proportional Derivative Control.
Our first attempt to control the equations
of motion of a robot will be something
called Inverse Dynamics Control.
We are introducing it first because in
some sense, it's the most obvious thing to
try, but we'll see often times it
doesn't work well in practice.
The idea here is that the motors can
generate arbitrary accelerations on
the system if they just cancel
out the natural dynamics.
By choosing torques and forces that cancel
everything out but the acceleration,
the actuator can, in theory,
make the system accelerate at its will.
Using this control technique,
we can get a system to go wherever
we want arbitrarily fast.
Let's give an example using pendulum-like
dynamics as they show up so
much in robotics.
Imagine that you're balancing a pendulum
on your hand and you want the pendulum to
point straight up, but you can only move
your hands side to side to balance it.
You may have tried this for
fun with a meter stick or a ruler.
This is system can be modeled by
a pendulum attached to a cart.
It can roll left or right, and where only
lateral forces can be applied to the cart.
Here's a simulation of inverse dynamical
control applied to a pendulum on a cart.
So you get the pendulum
to point straight up, or
be at an angle of theta
equals zero radians.
Remember, the only available input
we have to control the theta angle
is to push the cart left or right.
In this simulation things work out pretty
well, and we can cancel out the dynamics,
and accelerate the pendulum as
fast as we want to vertical.
But often in robotics,
we don't precisely know the dynamics.
Or the actual dynamics might not
exactly match the simplified model.
For example, a walking robot might look
approximately like a rimless wheel, but
in actuality, models never
exactly match the physical world.
If the control scheme doesn't account for
model uncertainty, problems can occur.
Here we wrote out the acceleration
using inverse dynamics control,
when the controller has an imperfect
estimate of the parameters,
here represented by matrices with tildes.
As you can see, the actual acceleration
is no longer the desired acceleration F.
Another possible issue with
inverting the dynamics for
control is that the forces needed to
cancel out the dynamics can be very high.
Notice how much the cart
gets pushed around.
In real life, actuators can be
very torque or power limited.
And often not enough actuators exist
to cancel out the natural dynamics.
As we've seen previously in this course,
often a better strategy in legged robotics
is to utilize the natural dynamics as much
as possible instead of canceling them out.
So as to minimize the needed motor torque.
Here's an example of the cart when
it has imperfect internal model of
their parameters.
As you can see, the pendulum falls over.
An extremely popular method of control
that is more robust to parameter
variations is called proportional
derivative control, or PD control.
A PD controller has two parts.
The first is the P part,
or proportional term.
The Proportional Controller tries to
push the system to a desired value
proportionally to the difference between
the actual and the desired value.
We call this difference the error.
So when the system is closed
to where it should be or
when the error is low the controller
slows down and doesn't push too hard.
But when it is very far away
the controller pushes much harder.
If you're a mechanical thinker, you might
imagine proportional control like a spring
pulling the system to a desired value,
included by the rest length of the spring.
A problem with just using
proportional control
is that it can drive the system
variable to a desired point, but
it doesn't do anything explicitly
to make sure it's stopped there.
In the case of our spring analogy, without
damping a spring constantly oscillates and
overshoots its rest length.
Here's the pendulum on the cart
using just proportional control.
The error does repeatedly go to zero, but
there's no natural damping in this system,
so the goal is continually overshot.
The d or derivative term adds damping to
the system to prevent this from happening.
The derivative term is proportional
to the change in error.
It tries to prevent the error
from changing too fast.
It can prevent the perpetual
overshoot problem we just mentioned.
This derivative term is then
added to the proportional term,
and the sum of these terms is
used as an input to this system.
Another way about thinking about PD
control is from an energy perspective.
Where we reimagine that the error term
as a virtual energy associated with it.
The potential part of the PD Controller
acts like forces from a potential field,
which can drive the error momentarily to
a certain position where its potential
energy is minimized.
But it can't change the total energy,
it will still have kinetic
energy at this point.
The derivative portion acts to dissipate
this energy, reducing the total energy so
that eventually the error goes
to zero with no kinetic energy.
Because of this, PD control could be
considered to be in a class of controllers
called potential dissipative
control that explicitly considers
this virtual energy landscape
that we've used as an analogy.
Here's the cart with the derivative
term added in to use full PD control.
Notice how the derivative term dampens out
the oscillations that we saw previously.
Since PD controllers use the state of
the system to formulate what to do,
they're a classic example
of feedback controllers.
PD control can work very
well in linear systems,
however most real-life
systems are non-linear.
Non-linear systems can act approximately
linear close to their equilibrium states.
So often in cases where a system's range
of operation is close to its equilibrium,
even if it is non-linear just as the
pendulum on a card example PD control can
work well.
Also, frequently another term is added
in which integrates the error in what is
called PID control.
Before we end we are going to review
the Raibert controller which we
introduced at the end of
the template section,
to show that PD control can be used
on real robots to great effect.
Recall that Raibert's hoppers were
approximately slip like machines that had
actuators capable of producing
leg twerks to vary the leg angle,
as well as radio leg forces.
Raibert's control idea was to
provide a constant radial force and
stance to get a vertical hop, to use
angular torque to control their body pitch
and to use the leg touchdown angle
to control that forward speed
through the natural body dynamics.
The forward speed controller is
a little more complicated, but
essentially uses proportional control.
The first term estimates how far ahead
of the body the foot should touch down
without causing a net forward
acceleration in stance.
And then the second term adds an offset
in proportion to the current speed error.
So that the robot accelerates
to the desired speed over time.
Often times in legged robotics
due to limited actuation,
the natural dynamics must
be taken into account.
And Raibert's control scheme demonstrates
that PD control can leverage
the natural dynamics through the use
of the forward speed controller to
achieve impressive performance.
We've covered a lot in this lecture.
But I hope it's given you a practical
introduction to some engineering
tools that will let you model in
control legged robots for yourself.
We've gone over the necessity
of understanding the dynamics of
legged robots.
And shown that you can write
down the equations and
motion directly from energy
using Lagrangian mechanics.
This process is often simpler
than using free-body diagrams and
more complicated systems, and
it can be easily automated in software.
Finally, we introduced proportional
derivative control as a way of controlling
these dynamics,
to get the robot to do what you want.