In this section,
we're going to consider actuators.
Actuators are very important in leg of
robots because this is how the robot
exerts forces on the world.
These forces conserve to either
manipulate the environment or
manipulate the robot itself.
We're going to consider different
actuation technologies, and
their respective advantages and
disadvantages.
The first actuator we'll think about
are hydraulics and pneumatics.
These are typically considered
as actuators, but really,
they're actually transmissions.
These transmissions rely
on a source of compressed
fluid that's usually external
to the actuators themselves.
For hydraulics, the working fuel is oil.
Where as for pneumatics,
the working fluid is typically air.
So, for both of these systems, the force
is proportional to the cross-section
area of the piston and the power consumed
is proportional to the velocity.
They have very good specific force and
specific power because of
the decoupled power source.
In this video, we have a very simple
example of a hydraulic system.
There are two syringes filled with fluid,
and
as one syringe moves, it causes
the other syringe to move as well.
The force on the syringes and
displacement both relate to
the surface area of the syringe.
In this video we see a simple
example of a pneumatic system
where moving one cylinder
causes the other to move.
The forces and displacement are also
proportional to the area, however,
because the fluid is compressible,
the relationship isn't as clear.
Friction in the walls of the cylinder
is responsible for this discrepancy.
The innate compliance of the two working
fluids dictates how the systems can work.
In this simple hydraulic system, if we tap
the end of the syringe so that the system
is closed It's almost impossible
to compress the hydraulic fluid.
In the pneumatic system, however, if we
cap the syringe, the compressible fluid
means that as we push on the cylinder,
we have effectively created an air spring.
These air springs were very useful
in Mark Raibert's early hoppers,
which were all pneumatic.
These pneumatic hoppers used
air as the working fluid.
And that's what's responsible for
the hopping you can see in this video.
However, the spring properties of the leg
are also due to
the compression of the air.
More recent Boston Dynamics robots
use hydraulic transmissions.
In this video,
we see Spot, which is a hydraulic
machine that has an electrical pump.
It's relatively quiet.
In this video, we see LS3, which also
has a hydraulic transmission, but
has a gas engine,
which makes it very loud.
[SOUND] Now we consider the implications
on actuation bandwidth
in these transmissions.
Actuation bandwidth is how the amplitude
of the signal decreases as
frequency increases.
Ideally, we would like very
high actuation bandwidth so
that we get significant
amplitude at high frequencies.
In this video, we see a simple pneumatic
system where one cylinder is actuated
externally and we see the implications
of movement in the other cylinder.
The larger cylinder is driven
at increasing speeds and
we can see that the amplitude in
the smaller cylinder decreases.
In this video we see a simple
hydraulic system where the larger
driven cylinder causes displacement
in the smaller cylinder.
As the frequency of the larger
cylinder's drive is increased,
the smaller cylinder's amplitude
decreases, but not as significantly.
This simple demonstration
shows the bandwidth advantages
of hydraulic compared
to pneumatic systems.
Now we consider electromagnetic actuators
typically exemplified by electric motors.
These motors have
considerably lower forces and
operate at very high speeds
with high bandwidth.
The power costs operate these
motors is typically proportional to
the torque squared.
The operation of these motors is
governed by a speed-torque curve.
This means that the peak torque
is achieved at no speed.
And as speed increases,
the provided torque linearly decreases.
This can be modeled with a force
damper system as seen in this image.
This force damper model is a useful
abstraction of the speed torque curve.
This speed torque curve can be simply
explained by a force damper model.
The force in this Model F is attenuated
by a damper with constant beat.
Again, we see that at no speed, the full
force of the actuator is available.
Whereas at larger speeds,
the damper diminishes the output force.
Most electric motors are used in legged
robots with the addition of a gear box.
The gearbox effectively increases
the output torque and decreases the speed.
This allows the maximum power
of the actuator to be achieved
at reasonable speeds.
While gears are very helpful to amplify
torque they are also fragile and lossy.
In gear boxes there's considerable static,
dry and viscous friction.
Furthermore the motor's inertia is
reflected through the gear box so
that the inertia at the output is
proportional to the gear ratio squared.
Gil Pratt made famous the notion
of a series elastic actuator
in which a spring is placed
between the load and the motor.
This is very helpful in that it
protects the gears from shock loading
It also improves the compliance
of the system and
it changes force control into
a position control problem.
By changing the effective
length of the spring
forces can be modulated when the actuator
is in contact with the load.
For a series elastic system we must add
a series spring to our four stamper model.
This spring of stiffness KS is added
between the actuator and the load.
So proprioception in legging robotics
is the information about one's own.
Information in this context is
typically a force on the end effector.
It's possible to measure forces with
an explicit sensor at the end effector.
But here we consider forces that are
inferred by displacements at the actuator.
For this to work,
actuator transparency is key,
so that information from the end effector
can travel to the actuator without being
significantly attenuated or delayed.
Most delays will come in from any
kind of compliance in the system,
such as a series elastic element.
Actuator transparency is much
improved by now removing the gearbox.
By removing the gearbox,
we decrease the attenuation by all the
sources of friction inside the gearbox.
These direct drive robots were first
pioneered by Harry Asada in the 80s.
These machines were, however,
not power-autonomous and needed to be
plugged into the ground as well as having
the first link attached to the ground.
In our Minotaur machine,
we have created a power-autonomous,
legged robot that is direct drive.
The actuators on the minuter machine
are conventional of the shelf
rotary brushless electric motors.
When comparing the actuators in
minuter to actuators in a Rex robot.
We see 100 fold decrease
in reflected inertia
a 50 fold decrease in viscous friction.
And a four-fold decrease in
both static and dry friction.
In this video, we see Minotaur taking
a few short steps before making a jump.
What's important to understand here is
that the machine must sense every time
the leg is in contact with the ground.
This is done using proprioception.
The actuators in the leg are commanded
to be virtual springs, and
as the leg hits the ground, the deflection
in the virtual springs is measured and
a force at the end effector is estimated.
As you can see, this works reliably and
ground detection is sensed near
the beginning of the stride.
In this video,
we see a comparison between two actuators
with very different transparency.
One is direct drive and one has a gearbox.
First we see the direct drive motor,
which is not controlled in any way,
being driven into a fragile egg.
We see that the egg does not crack and
that the actuator itself spins.
This spinning means that
position information
can go back into the other system.
In the second part of this video,
we see that a conventional
motor with a gear box is driven
at a similar speed into the egg.
We notice that the egg breaks and
that the actuator has not rotated at all.
This means that no information
can get from the end effector
back into the system.
Now we consider what happens in biology.
Muscles in humans are typically
very high in transparency.
If we consider our series elastic
spring damper model from before,
the typical hill muscle model
is very similar looking.
But, has the addition of a parallel
spring of spring constant kp.
Muscles also have proprioceptive sensors
built in as the muscle spindles can sense
the change in length and the Golgi
tendon can sense tension in the muscle.
In this section we considered
the advantages and
disadvantages of various
actuators technologies.
Furthermore we motivated why
it's important to think about
not only how the actuators are able
to exert forces on their environment.
But what happens when the environment
exerts forces onto the actuator?