[MUSIC]
Welcome to the special module on
mobility within the Robotics MOOC at
the University of Pennsylvania.
In this course, we're going to spend
four weeks talking about mobility.
In week one, we'll quickly,
quickly understand that the animals
are the key to mobility and
we'll focus on limb mobility.
And we'll realize to get that right,
we need to think about physics and energy,
and the exchange of work.
In week two,
we'll break down the components.
Behavioral components like this pogo
stick that we'll be talking about,
and physical components like
these strength of materials and
structural properties that
we'll be talking about.
Don't worry.
We're going to be thinking about
how to put them together and
build bodies with limbs out of
these components in week three.
We'll think about kinematics which is
the study of the way limbs move in space.
We'll add dynamics and so you can begin to
think about these hopping machines that
use pogo stick like ideas even though they
don't look very much like pogo sticks.
Finally, in week 4 we'll be ready to talk
about what's known of programming work.
How do you compose more complicated
behaviors out of simple pieces?
And these energy bases begin to be shaped.
And as they're shaped properly, we begin
to snap together different components.
And as we snap together these simpler
components into more complicated bodies,
we anchor them into the behaviors
that we really wish to achieve.
Here's an example of the horizons
of research, Aaron Johnson's
leaping robot trying to scramble
up the ledge of a table.
Welcome to the mobility
component of the robotics
specialization MOOC by the University
of Pennsylvania Grasp Laboratory.