[MUSIC]
Welcome to the first week of our
special robotic course in mobility.
This week we are going to be looking
at the background materials, and
we'll be motivating the effort.
Our first segment will involve
motivation and such questions as why,
how, where to move.
We'll spend a fair bit of time
thinking about the animals, and
we'll talk a fair bit
about bioinspiration.
And finally,
we'll move toward what it means for
robots to take bioinspiration and
turn that inspiration into engineering.
At that end of that first segment,
we'll be looking at animals that don't use
their limbs, and realizing that now,
most of the animals do use their limbs.
And we'll be spending the rest of our
MOOC time on limbed and tailed mobility.
The second half hour of this week
will be background material.
Those of you who are very strong on
ordinary differential equations and
linear algebra will race
through this segment.
And those of you who are weak are going
to find it important to take some time
to go through and think about the ideas
being introduced, and possibly to do
some background reading as well, in order
to follow the development of the ideas.
Really, it revolves around this simple
second-order differential equation that
most college students have in year two or
year three in engineering, and
even in other disciplines as well.
We'll be thinking about this
second-order mechanical
differential equation
as a dynamical system.
And that change in thinking takes a little
bit of getting used to, as exemplified by
these figures where on the left-hand side
of each panel you see a time trajectory.
And on the right hand side, you see
the position and the velocity on a plane.
And time is collapsed
down onto that plane so
that the trajectories in time become
orbits, so-called curves on the plane.
That idea is crucial.
We're not really concerned with linear
ordinary differential equations,
which is what you all learned in
your sophomore or junior year.
No, no, everything that's interesting
about mobility in robotics has to do with
nonlinear ordinary differential equations.
And we'll spend some time reviewing what's
known about nonlinear dynamical systems.
The most important ideas that we'll need
later have to with energy and basins.
Welcome to week one.
We'll be spending the rest of
the three weeks using these ideas and
turning them into marvelous robots, and
thinking about how our marvelous
robots might become even better.