In this section, we consider
the implications on strength, mass, and
other properties when changing lens scale.
Here we see two similar triangles.
They are similar because the angles a,
b, and c are all equal.
However, one triangle has side length
L and the other has side length 2L.
Now we consider the implications on
some properties of these triangles.
Since the perimeter is
simply the sum of the sides,
the perimeter of the larger triangle will
be double that of the small triangle.
So the perimeter will scale
linearly with the lens.
The area of the triangles, however,
scales according to length squared.
This motivates the much more general field
of scaling analysis, and specifically
dynamic scaling and dynamic similarity,
which are very useful in robotics.
Now instead of triangles, we consider
what happens when you scale cubes.
As expected, the area of the cubes is
proportional to the length squared,
and the volume of the cubes is
proportional to the length cubed.
As you can see,
a cube with side length two L, and
be thought of as containing eight
smaller cubes of side length, L.
Suppose you have two ice cubes,
one of side length, L, and
one of side length, 2L, and
they're sitting in the sun.
For these ice cubes, the heat that goes
into them is proportional to their surface
area and the thermal mass of the ice
cubes is proportional to their volume.
So now scaling will help us answer the
question which ice cube will melt first
and by what factor.
As well as helping us make predictions
about what will happen with even larger or
smaller ice cubes.
Galileo was also very curious about
the implications of scaling in animals.
He observed that bones of different
sizes had different proportions.
In this figure,
we see one of Galileo's sketches,
in which he draws a smaller bone and
a larger bone, where the larger bone
is disproportionately thicker
than the smaller bone.
The question he asked is if a larger
bone that is three times the length
of the smaller bone were to
experience the same stresses
in a larger animal as
compared to a smaller animal.
How much disproportionately thicker
did the larger bone need to be.
Just preserving cross-sectional
area as the bone scales
does not however tell the whole story.
Larger animals typically
move relatively more slowly
as measured in body length per
second compared to smaller animals.
Furthermore, larger animals typically
adopts a less probe posture
than smaller animals.
We now consider how a change in posture
influences a change in loading of
a cartoon of a bone.
There are five fundamental
types of loading.
Compression is a force parallel
to the axis of the bone,
where the bone is being pushed together.
Tension is also parallel to the axis of
the bone, but it is being pulled apart.
Shear is perpendicular to the axis of
the bone as if it is being slid apart.
Bending is a result of a force
perpendicular to the axis of the bone
coming out of the screen
that is being twisted.
Torsion is the result of a twisting
motion, but parallel with the bone.
Here we introduce a fundamental notion of
stress, which is force normalized by area.
Stress is a very important consideration.
Depending on how a part is being loaded,
there's a certain stress
at which it must break.