In this section we aim to qualify
the failure mode of materials,
as well as understanding how to
shape them into desired parts.
There are two main material types,
brittle materials and ductile materials.
In this video we see acrylic plastic,
a brittle material.
The sample is being bent more and
more, until it fails catastrophically.
In this video we see a ductile material,
aluminum, that is being
bent in a similar way.
The aluminum bends, and
it can deform permanently, known as
plastic deformation, before it breaks.
The materials in this section are all
isotropic, meaning that they respond
the same way to stimulus that
comes in different directions.
Now we will learn about
a stress strain curve.
Stress, as we learned in the previous
section, is force normalized by area.
Stress is typically referred
to by the Greek letter sigma.
Strain is displacement normalized
by nominal length of the material.
Strain is normally referred to
by the Greek letter epsilon.
In this figure we see
a stress strain curve for
a brittle material,
such as acrylic in the previous video.
The slope of this line, denoted e, is
the Young's modulus, or elastic modulus.
In this figure we see the stress
strain curve for a ductile material.
Once again, as in the brittle material,
there's a linear region,
up to point 1, which is the yield
strength of the material.
If the yield strength is exceeded,
we start to see plastic or
permanent deformation of the material.
As the stress increases,
we now see nonlinear deformation,
up to point 3, which is the ultimate
strength of the material.
If this ultimate strength is exceeded,
the material will break.
If the material experiences a sustained
stress between the yield strength and
the ultimate strength as seen in point 1*,
permanent plastic deformation will occur.
When the material is unloaded, the strain
will decrease with slope e again.
This material has now
deformed plastically.
Now when the material is loaded again,
the nonlinear region will only only
start at stresses exceeding 1*.
This is known as strain hardening.
Now that we understand how
some materials respond,
how do we make them into
the desired part shape?
First we consider more conventional
subtractive manufacturing.
Subtractive manufacturing
is like sculpting.
You start with a large block of material
and cut away what is not desired.
In this video we see a computer-controlled
milling machine cutting out a guitar
from a large block of
multiple kinds of wood.
In this video we see a laser cutter
burning through some ABS plastic and
cutting out a desired
two-dimensional shape.
Typically, subtractive manufacturing is
also joined by an assembly step in which
many smaller parts are combined
together using fasteners.
More recently we have seen a rise
in additive manufacturing,
notably 3D printing.
Additive manufacturing necessarily
has a smaller material palette,
as it relies on the properties of
the materials themselves to form the part.
In this video we see a stereo lithographic
3D printer, which uses a UV-curable resin.
The resin is selectively cured in
layers onto a moveable platform, and
is pulled out of the bath.
In this video we see a 3D printer that
relies on fuse deposition manufacturing.
Here a polymer is heated past its
glass-transition temperature and
is deposited layer by layer
onto the build plate.
One significant advantage of 3D printing
is that complexity is almost free.
Typically, the time and
cost of the print is only proportional
to the volume of material used.
Sometimes sacrificial
support material is needed
when the part has significant overhangs,
as can be seen in this image.
In the construction of our
robots we typically prefer
2D manufacturing processes
that are cheap and
readily available that can then
be combined into 3D machines.
In this figure we see the Minitaur and
Jerboa robots that were predominately
manufactured using 2D techniques and
then assembled into full 3D machines.
I would now like to highlight three
techniques that are used to facilitate
this assembly.
These are finger joints,
square nuts, and standoffs.
In this image we see two
water jet aluminum plates
that are perpendicularly connected.
Finger joints are used so that there
is significant overlapping material
to prevent any failure
due to shear stress.
Captive square nuts are used to
facilitate the manufacturing process so
that no tapping has to be done.
A cut out is simply made the right size so
that a square nut can be
pressed into the part.
In this image we see a standoff being
used to provide two parallel planes.
Standoffs can be threaded or
unthreaded and
greatly speed up assembly time as it
prevents manual tapping once again.