In this section, we consider basic
material properties relevant to design.
Material properties of interest, such
as strength and stiffness are typically
mass normalized and specific strength and
specific stiffness computed.
In this figure,
we see a log log plot of youngs modulus or
stiffness plotted against density.
In the top right,
we see that there are many metals
at the very favorable high stiffness
at the price of significant density.
Moving down in stiffness, we see many
ceramics that seem favorable, but
are typically very brittle.
Moving down in stiffness
a little bit more,
we see composite materials, which will
be of interest later in this section.
We now revisit the implications of posture
on stress in a simplified bone model.
In this figure,
we see how changes in posture influence
loading in bones in a simplified model.
For a more upright posture,
there is nearly pure compressive loading.
This results in a uniform
stress distribution,
which in our example does not exceed
the ultimate strength of the material.
In the more sprawled animal, we see
a combination of compression and bending.
The principle of superposition let's us
simply add the stress profiles to see
the resulting profile on the right.
This resulting profile has peak
stress above the ultimate strength
of the material.
And so in this case, the bone in
the sprawled animal would break.
As mentioned, all materials up to
this point have been isotropic.
Which means when loaded in different
conditions, they respond the same way.
We now consider anisotropic
materials such as composites,
which have very different responses
depending on loading conditions.
In this video, we see an example
of an anisotropic material that
has a grain similar to
something like wood.
When the material is loaded in
the direction of the grain,
it is very compliant.
When it is rotated 90 degrees,
however and loaded against the grain,
it becomes very rigid.
In this video,
we see the implications of combining
two of these samples in different ways.
When the two samples are combines with
that the grains are parallel, once again,
the combined samples are very compliant
when loaded in the direction of the grain.
When the samples are combined, so
that the grains are perpendicular.
We now have a more isotropic material,
which is stiff in both directions.
In this image, we see the robot XRL that
has two different kind of composites.
These composites are layered differently
to achieve different material properties.
In both cases,
we would like the ultimate strength of
the material to be as high as possible.
In the shell, however,
we prioritize stiffness.
And in the legs, we prioritize compliance.
Now, we consider anisotropic
materials at various scales.
These are known as
hierarchical structures.
In this figure,
we see hierarchical structures found
in nature, such as bone and bamboo.
These are both examples of
using hierarchical features
to change the property of
the overall material as distinct
from the material properties
of the constituents.
In this figure,
we see the use of hierarchical compliance
in the sticky bot robot, which is able
to keep the toes of the machine a fixed
to a surface, even on irregular terrain.