In week one,
Dan talked to you about basins and energy.
Remember that gradient-like
systems like to flow downhill.
So what does this hill mean?
For a passive mechanical system, this hill
could just be the total mechanical energy
of the system, which doesn't increase,
but decreases because of friction or
other actuated control inputs.
Here I;ve have drawn a cartoon
of a hill might look like.
So, the actual state of the system
is down below on the plane and
the hill signifies how the states
kind of roll down the hill.
The basin is the rim of the funnel which
is all the states that are kind of
funneled through into the goal location,
but what if now we have multiple funnels?
So instead of just rolling down one,
we could have the states
roll down one funnel, then into a second
one, and then into a third one, etcetera.
This simple cartoon is really the idea
behind sequential composition, or
back-chaining basins.
The only rule, really, is that
the goal location of the first funnel
has to be within the basin
of the second funnel.
That's it, it's very simple and intuitive,
but it's been used a lot in robotics.
Here's an example of a juggling robot,
where this idea was used to transition
between bouncing the ball and
palming the ball to make it stop.
This is not the only use
of sequential composition.
Way back in 1984, a famous paper by
Lozano, Perez, Mason, and Taylor
described how sequential composition might
be used to automate factory floor tasks.
This is a peg in hole assembly task ,where
for instance, in the center right image,
a successful assembly might
entail moving the peg down,
sliding it across to the left,
and then down into the hole.
This strategy, it'll be obvious to you,
doesn't work for the center image, for
instance.
So what we're really doing is
composing a sequence of maneuvers for
the peg that ensure that
the assembly will proceed correctly.
Another assembly like example is this one,
where what we're trying to do is
go to a known final configuration for
these hex keys.
That actuated control input here is the
actuation of the tray underneath the hex
keys and so by tilting the trays through
a sequence of maneuvers, we can channel or
funnel the hex key through different
configurations into a desired final one.
This is also work by Matt Mason.
This is a more modern example
where optimization and
robust control ideas have come in.
What the researchers are doing is online
motion planning, that is they're selecting
appropriate funnels prepared by the
current state of this glider online and
using that to control it
through unknown obstacles.
The side effect is acute in
control objectives sequentially.
If we were to have
executed them in parallel,
that idea is called parallel composition.
There's going to be a lot more
about this in section 4.2,
but here's a quick recap of the origin and
history.
So let's say we build on the juggle
that I showed you two slides ago.
What if we wanted to now juggle
two balls instead of one?
So this is really a parallel
composition of the same controller.
But there's an interesting twist on this.
If you think about the ball-ball paddle
state space there's a big obstacle
if the two balls are falling
simultaneously because the paddle can't
hit both balls at the same time.
So what we're really doing is
composing the two controllers but
avoiding the obstacle of the phase
of the two balls being aligned.
Another example is
Raibert's planer hopper,
which Jeff talked to you about last week.
What Raibert did is he thought about
the vertical hopping control and
the forward speed control, and
the pitch control separately, and
played them all out together.
There are no similar obstacles
in this situation, but
that's an interesting
thing to keep in mind.
To summarize, robot control can be thought
of as floating downhill on artificial
energy functions.
Sequential composition
formalizes a sequence of tasks
using back-chaning of basins.
We can sequence course manipulation or
assembly tasks and there have been several
other examples in the literature
that I haven't had time to cover.
Parallel composition describes satisfying
multiple control objectives at
the same time.
What we have to keep in mind with parallel
composition is that there are obstacles
introduced into the state
space that might not have been
there without the composition.
And secondly we have to keep in mind that
lots of systems inject coupling forces
that would either have to be cancelled or
thought about appropriately.
We're going to talk a lot more about
parallel composition in the next segment.