In this segment we'll take a look
at some lessons from biology that
have been helpful for
robotics strategic design robots.
There won't be too much formalism in this
section not least because the design is
very hard to formalize.
You should expect this segment
to be at a fairly high level.
Because we won't have time to delve
too much into details anyways.
Personally, for
me as a roboticist in training,
going to conferences with biomechanists
has taught me things that I wouldn't have
learned from engineering courses or
engineering conferences.
And I hope to share some of that with you.
The three segments are for three
broad classes of terrestrial runners,
each of which have representative
robots in our lab.
First step,
we'll look at sprawled posture runners.
First, what are sprawled posture runners?
As these cartoons are showing you,
sprawled runners have horizontal upper
limb segments whereas upright animals
have more vertical upper limb segments.
What this means is that
the center of mass height for
sprawled posture runners
is usually much lower.
So h1 is typically much larger
than h2 in the images here.
Typical sprawled posture runners
are cockroaches, spiders, crabs, etc.
You might wonder why all of these
animals have more legs than dogs, or
horses or upright posture runners.
Alexander gave a very nice argument for
why this might be true.
Let's assume that the center
of mass is at height eight,
where we just discussed that
posture runners are usually lower.
So you can calculate
the time that it would take
an animal at height 8
to fall to the ground.
It's a simple application
of first year physics.
Given a stride frequency f, the reaction
time for the animal to correct for
the fall is sigma,
stride periods as given by this equation.
Using some numerical values for
a cockroach and a dog hopefully you'll
see what Alexander is getting at.
Assuming Alexander is correct and
the greater number of legs is for
some kind of stability.
Should we assume that cockroaches
always move precise statically?
For one,
cockroaches are tremendously fast.
Cockroaches can run at up to
50 body lengths per second.
A cheetah, for comparison,
runs at 16 body lengths per second.
Cheetahs are known for
being the fastest land animals and
probably what you think of when
you think of a fast animal.
Additionally, some bio-mechanics research,
that's referenced in the side,
shows quite a few things about cockroaches
that you might be surprised by.
They found that static assumptions
are completely insufficient to explain
stability of cockroaches at
their fastest running speeds.
Firstly, the duty factors of
running went down to less than 0.5.
The duty factor is what percent of stride
a leg is in contact with the ground.
Cockroaches use a virtual biped gait, and
a duty factor of less than 0.5 means that
there must be some amount of time for
which both of its virtual
legs are in the air.
The distance from the center of mass
to the edge of the support polygon,
which is the polygon made up of
the three legs on the ground for
a cockroach,
is less than zero at the highest speeds,
which means the center of mass is
completely outside its support polygon.
Now that we know that cockroaches
move quite dynamically,
do they actively stabilize
these dynamic gaits?
Spanberg and
Full ran cockroaches over flat ground and
ground with irregular blocks up to three
times the hip height of the cockroach.
This definitely qualifies
as quite rough terrain.
And they recorded the muscle potentials
of the cockroaches as it was running at
fairly high speeds over these
different kinds of terrain.
The first surprising finding is that
even over the rough terrain, cockroaches
reduced their speed by less than 20% even
as they received large prohibitions.
Secondly, they found that the neurosignals
going to the muscles of the cockroach
didn't vary much at all between the rough
terrain and the very flat terrain.
What this means is that the descending
control signals that the cockroach muscles
receive aren't really varying that
much when the type of terrain changes.
The susceptibility of the cockroach
must be explained by mechanical feedback
that's set by feet forward activation.
The next question you might be wondering
about are why cockroach legs are splayed
as they are shown in this image.
The legs in insects are typically either
levers or they're inclined struts.
The front legs act more as levers,
which means that they experience
large tangential moments.
Whereas the rear legs are usually struts,
which means they act more
just in axial directions.
The ground reaction force patterns of
cockroaches as they run over force plates
shows that there are large
horizontal forces,
even if they're running
at a constant speed.
What does this mean?
Are the cockroaches needlessly
slowing themselves down and
accelerating themselves every stride?
Did this analysis and showed that
the horizontal forces actually have
a significant effect in terms of
the movements around the joints.
As you can see, the rear legs
contact the ground at a point not
directly vertically below
where the rear hips are.
And so directing the ground reaction force
to a point closer to the hips minimizes
the movement about the joints.
In summary, we have learned a little bit
that cockroaches don't use their brains
for much, but have bodies very
finely tuned for how they move.
In fact, how they move almost defines how
cockroaches are built and how they look.
We have not even gotten into
microstructures, construction materials,
etc., but the common theme is that
locomotion is a big factor in
how cockroaches are designed.
And this is true for animals in general.
Now let's look at some artificial or
man-made sprawled posture runners.
If we sample the hexipedal
robots in the world,
we'll find a ton that look like this.
They have fully articulated joints and
lots of degrees of freedom.
With so many actuated joints,
unfortunately, they'll have to
rely on quasistatic stability.
However, we learned before that
cockroaches move in a very dynamic way,
and they use mechanical
passive stabilization.
There are some robots that attempt to
embody these biomechanical principles,
the first among which is RHex.
Which of these do you think
looks more like the cockroach?
So what does it mean to have
mechanical passive stabilization in
terms of engineering?
Specifically, what
are the implications on design?
As Jeff described in week two, walking
is an exchange of kinetic energy and
gravitational potential energy.
So they typically isolate out of phase.
Where as running, hopping and
trotting display an inface kinetic and
potential energy oscillation.
So what does this mean?
Where is the energy going in
the values of potential and
kinetic energy, when animals are running?
The answer is that the energy is
stored in elastic potential energy.
So for running, you really need
compliance either physical or virtual.
Not just that, Blickhan showed that
the leg force versus extension,
the effective stiffness of the leg,
is also roughly mass independent for
a very large range of animals.
So the relative stiffness per leg is
conserve and different gates use different
numbers of legs which determine
the overall system stiffness.
These lessons tell us
a lot about the virtual or
physical compliance that is expected to be
required when you're designing your robot.
So how was this implemented on RHex?
One of the first things you'll
probably notice about RHex is the C
shaped leg design, which is on more
modern iterations of this robot.
The benefits of this C
shaped leg are numerous.
The first is that it provides an easy
way to add compliance to the system,
without having too many moving parts.
In fact,
the whole leg is one mechanical part.
But it gives us compliance.
It's relatively easy to manufacture.
It gives us rolling contact,
which makes our leg look more
like a wheel in some situations.
The C shape also provides an effectively
increasing mechanical advantage.
Effective Mechanical Advantage or
EMA is something Gavin talked
about in the previous segment.
And you can think about how this would
be useful for RHex to be leaping.
There's a lot more on the conceptual
development of RHex coming up in
the next segment, so
I will not spend too much time on it now.
Here's a question,
should all of the legs of your
hexapedal robot have the same design?
The robot that you see running around in
this video quite fast, is called iSprawl.
iSprawl was designed at Stanford,
and it's a .3 kg, but
15 body lengths per second
open loop controlled robot.
This robot has explicit differentiation
between its front and rear legs.
So the rear legs tend
to accelerate the robot
where as the front legs tend to brake and
stabilize.
The actuator degrees of freedom on this
robot are radio histen leg motions
whereas there is significant
passive rotational stiffness.
So to summarize, biomechanics
tells us that sprawled animals
might need more legs because of
quasi static stability reasons.
But at the same time, they're not limited
to this, and they run quite dynamically.
They don't use active
control of their degrees of
freedom much when running
at the highest speeds.
From these lessons,
roboticists learn that dynamic
locomotion offers lots of advantages.
For instance,
you don't have to carefully plan your
footsteps because the mechanical self
stabilization should play a large part in
preventing the robot from falling over.
It's important to think of
energy exchange to run,
which means that you might often have
to think about things like compliance.
So now that we've learned these lessons,
do robots really needs six legs?
As we know from Alexander,
an upright machine with any reasonable
strike frequency can avoid falling.
And also we know that
quasistatic stability is not
all that important in the end.
In the next segment,
we'll look at quadrupeds.