So what's different in a quadruped from
the sprawled that we just looked at?
As you might have guessed,
quadrupeds are animals that use four legs.
This is distinct from tetrapods.
Tetrapods are evolutionarily
animals with four legs but
they don't necessarily use them, whereas
quadrupeds move around with four legs.
The leg and
foot structure is much more pronounced in
quadrupeds than sprawled posture runners.
In fact, we see three broad varieties,
unguligrade, digitigrade and plantigrade.
The unguligrades stand on the tips
of their toes, for instance, horses,
cattle, pigs and deer.
Digitigrade animals stand on
their toes for instance, cats,
dogs, dinosaurs, elephants, etc.
And plantigrade animals stand
on their entire foot, for
instance, bears, mice, humans, etc.
Additionally, their tendons and muscles
form viscoelastic structures that can be
modeled quite well,
as in this paper from Winters.
Almost all quadrupeds gallop
at their highest speeds.
Galloping is a gait which has pronounced
extension of the stride length
which is caused mostly by
an extension of the spine.
Additionally, we start to
see things like tails.
We'll learn more about tails
in the section on bipeds.
But tails in these quadrupeds also
help turning and reorientation.
We saw that sprawl posture runners almost
exclusively used an alternating tripod,
virtual biped gait.
But gaits in quadrupeds are much
more interesting and varied.
Almost all quadrupeds walk
at their lowest speeds and
almost all of them gallop
at their highest speeds.
But in the middle there's a large
variety of gaits that can be observed.
I want to show you some popular
descriptions of gaits that
appear in biomechanics, so
that you can visually see these diagrams
and understand what is being said.
On the left is the limb support patterns
description that you'll find in some
literature.
The field in that represents leg stance
and along the horizontal axis is time.
On the right, is the Gait diagram
description where again the field in bars
are legs uncontacted to the ground and the
not filled in bars are legs in the air.
The Gait diagram description on the right,
gives a much better
idea of the duty cycle,
which is exactly how much time the leg
spends on the ground versus in the air.
You should be able to look
at these diagrams and
have an idea of how the legs come in
contact with the ground for various gaits.
Now that we've seen a few different gaits,
why do they exist?
Why do quadrupeds display different ones?
Why do they just pick the best one and
stick with it?
The primary reason is really energetic.
Energetic efficiency in biomechanics is
often measured by the cost of transport,
which is given by this formula here.
The numerator is the metabolic power
consumed by the animal and at the bottom
is some measure of the speed at which the
animal is moving normalized by its mass.
There are mechanical reasons that some
gaits were more energetically efficient.
For instance, a spring mass system has
a preferred oscillation frequency,
together with the stride frequency,
this might determine which gate is
more preferred at widths speed.
Other things that affect selection
of gaits include, limited speed and
limited force that can
produced by animal legs.
Now that we've seen some
quadrupedal animals,
let's look at some quadrupedal robots.
One of the most famous robotics
companies in the world
is at the erstwhile Boston Dynamics.
And they produced a range of quadrupeds,
from LitttleDog,
all the way to the LS3 robot
across a range of size scales.
These robots are hydraulic and
this comes with some of the advantages and
disadvantages that Gavin
mentioned in his segment.
This is an electromechanical quadruped,
the MIT Cheetah.
It's designed for
having a very transparent drive train and
accurate torque control,
which enables simple control strategies.
This robot is called StarlETH.
It's a series elastic
quadruped developed by ETH.
There are many more but we would like to
talk about the robot we have in our lab.
This is Minitaur,
one of our very own quadripeds.
It has a very unique leg design which
was designed to optimize a vertical
jumping task and is very good at that.
It's also one of the very few direct
drive legged robots in the world.
Electric motors typically like
operating at very high speeds but
don't give you very high forces
unless you had a gear box.
But careful design choices in a number
of areas has let us make a direct
drive legged robot which has
adequate force capabilities.
You'll see some of its feats of
performance in the last segment.
To go into the details
of mandatory design,
let's remember what we've learned about
animal legs in the past few segments.
For running,
legs should be able to store energy.
The legs should be able
to extend actively.
Additionally, there's a lot of evidence
that animals increase their effective leg
stiffness as they run.
Here's a plot of human data which
shows an almost linear relationship
between effective leg stiffness and
running speed.
Here are some linkage based
two degree freedom leg designs
with two actuators per leg.
Leg extension is an actively controlled
degree of freedom with any of these
designs.
An active compliance or
impedance control is also possible.
These three designs have different
performance with respect to metrics such
as intermittent force Studies D force,
and proprioception.
And you can find out more in this paper we
wrote about direct-drive legged robots.
To summarize, Biomechanists tell us
that legs need to swing and retract.
And gaits emerge from energetics and
control needs.
We roboticists have learned to build
legs with enough degrees of freedom and
we've learned several control ideas,
some of which we'll talk about
in the last week of the course.
Spines and tails haven't become that
popular yet in quadrupedal robots but
it's a burgeoning field and
I'm sure we'll see more of them.