Now we're moving on to bipeds.
We saw that some of the quadrupeds that
we talked about were quite accomplished
animals, as well as robots.
What is a reason for us to move to bipeds?
For animals,
manipulation is actually a key motivator.
Animals would have liked to use their
full limbs to manipulate optics and
not just walk around.
They developed an upright posture which
is known as orthograde versus pronograde.
They developed muscles for
supporting their core to be upright and
they also develop mechanisms for
endurance.
It's very curious that humans are actually
one of the best marathon runners in
the world, whereas even your house cat
could probably outrun you in a sprint.
That's because bipeds
developed mechanisms for
endurance that a lot of
quadrupeds can't have.
One of the reasons for
this has been termed carrier's constraint.
In a pronorate animal the forelimb muscles
are connected very close to the lungs.
What happens because of this
is that the stride rate
is coupled to the breathing rate.
So the biomechanical energetics,
i.e the stride length and
stride length, compete with the preferred
breathing rate for the animal.
Paleontologist Richard Cowen wrote this
funny limerick to help you remember
this fact.
You can see in this plot the horse's cost
of transport given by the dotted line
versus a human's cost of transport
you can see the human has
a very flat cost of transport
past a certain speed.
That's where it's running.
And since the human can alter its
breathing rate independent of stride rate,
the cost of transport can
remain relatively flat,
whereas the same is not true of the horse.
One disadvantage of bipeds,
as you might have guessed,
is that much more active
control of balance is required.
A standing biped is really an inverted
angelum that requires more active control
that a quadruped roll past the runner.
To double my balance a bit
more quasi statics ability
with the polygon of support is
basically impossible to temp of biped
because the best case is polygon
of support is just the line.
We humans often use our arms
inertially to help them balance.
If a mean friend walked up behind you and
gave you a shove, you might use your
arms to transfer your angular momentum and
stay upright or if you're walking
on a tightrope, you might use your arms to
exert counter movements about your torso.
Some bipeds have a purpose built
inertial appendage a tail, but
it's uses are more varied
than you may think.
Here's a video of a hopping
kangaroo where if you look closely,
you'll notice that the tail
seems to rotate opposite
to the direction that that
the leg is rotating in flight.
Why is this?
Here's a cartoon of a kangaroo.
This is from Mark Wayburg's paper.
If you imagine the body in flight as
being kind of a three link system,
with the tail being approximately one
link, the leg being one link, and
the body being the third link.
When the animal is trying to
recirculate its leg forward in flight
moving the tail in the opposite direction
cancels out the moment applied by leg and
keeps the body relatively level but in
the engineering we can both very light and
strong limbs which means that
the inertia of the leg can be small.
Do we still need the tail for this reason?
This is a kangaroo behavior you
might not have seen before.
They use their tail as a fifth leg.
This gate is called a pentopetal crawl,
and
it only happens at the slowest
speeds of movement of a Kangaroo.
But what it's doing is it's trying
to maintain a tripod of support
with every step.
Moving on to robotic bipeds, There's
a very crowded space of bipedal robots.
Part of the reason for this is that
there is a push to get human-like robots
out into the world doing
human-like things.
Close to the extreme end,
you'll find this robot, which has close
to 100 actuated degrees of freedom.
While this robot is very dexterous and has
a lot of fine manipulation capabilities
all the actuated degrees
of freedom need mass, and
not all of the degrees of freedom
can be useful for every task.
So we're stuck with a relatively low
power density and quasi static motions,
unfortunately.
We'll talk about some ways of
controlling walking in these settings
in a couple of slides.
Recently there's only be a push
towards actuated bipeds which have
a more reasonable chance of being able
to move dynamically through the world.
ATRIAS is probably the most
well known of this and
it uses a series of elastic
two degree freedom legs.
We asked this question before about by
an animal would like to be a biped versus
a quadruped but a lot of those
reasons like manipulation constraints,
etc don't really apply to robots at all.
So what are some reasons that
robots might want to be bipedal?
Gavin talked about scaling in Segment 2.2.
Here's a quick application of these
techniques to see if it's better to have
a trotting quadruped or a running biped.
Let's assume the amount of motor mass
you're allowed to have in your robot
is fixed.
But this mass can be
divided among end motors.
For instance, n would be two for
a trotting quadruped, if it were one for
a running biped.
This reference paper from Sanbay Kim's
group teaches us how the torque and
mass per motor scale with
the gap radius of the motor.
Eliminating our gap, we see that
the torque scale is the reciprocal of n.
What this means is that there is
a technological pressure towards having
fewer actuated degrees of freedom
driven by the specific force, scaling,
but the number of motors.
How does biped design affect control?
Before we move to control of
bipeds with low degrees of freedom
I wanted to go quickly over the control
ideas helpful for bipeds with feet, and
typically high degree
of freedom humanoids.
The first idea tries to reuse
the polygon of support idea.
It seems reasonable to try to
reuse the polygon of support idea,
because the foot is
really a small polygon.
The first thought might be to place
the center of mass above the polygon
created by the foot.
A popular generalization
of this is to use the so
called zero moment point
instead of the center of mass.
What the zero moment point does is
it incorporates inertial forces
as well as gravitational forces.
In this cartoon which
shows the ZMP the center
of mass is adjusted to take into
account horizontal acceleration of
the center of mass of the body
was just denoted by the cart.
Under actuated dynamic bipeds mostly
use a slip like control idea,
like Jeff spoke about it
in the previous segment.
The leg is modelled as a sprung mass.
The balance problem is to keep
the center of mass from toppling.
Raibert's idea was to notice that
there's a special touch toe angle
which causes neutral stance.
Intuitively replacing the toe under
the average position of the body
as it moves through a stance.
In addition to this strategy,
slip can actually be stabilized
by a fixed touchdown angle.
This is a controller that requires
no information and no sensing, but
can stabilize slip.
The simply stabilized strategy has,
unfortunately,
a smaller basin of attraction
than the Raibert strategy.
The bipedal we have in our
lab is called the Jerboa.
It's a robot with two legs and
a two degree of freedom actuated tail.
The tail masses only 6% of
the total mass of the body where
you'll see that it's quite effective.
The tail is a five bar linkage
in a spherical configuration.
We can see in this video how the two
motors control the two angles of the tail.
This allows the tail to provide horizontal
plain activation to the Jerboa.
Some ways in which a tail actuator is
better for an electro-mechanical robot
is that the tail operation can
happen at a higher duty cycle.
Legs can exert forces on the body
only when it's touching the ground.
Where as the tail can apply force to the
body even when the robot is in the air.
Additionally, the reaction forces from
the tail are independent of the traction
available on the ground.
Compare to the tail, the lengths
of jerboa are relatively simple.
They're only actually begin at the hip.
And the extension degree of
freedom is completely passive.
In this image, you will see that
there is a four-bar linkage for
the leg where a spring is controlling
the passive extension degree of freedom.
So now that we've endowed Jerboa
with a relatively complicated and
powerful tail,
what are some uses of a robotic tail?
The tail can impart movements
about the vertical axis,
which aids in turning as
you can see in this video.
In the sagittal plane,
the tail can reorient the body pitch.
Again, the tail only has
6% of the body mass.
But you can see that it's very
effective at correcting the body.
In addition to the sagittal reorientation,
we are currently working on
spatial reorientation as well.
Which would be possible because of the two
degree of freedom tail that Jerboa has.
We'll learn a lot more about Jerboa
behaviors in the next segment.
To summarize, from biomechanists,
we learned that animals went bipedal for
mostly physiological reasons.
It's interesting that as roboticists,
we learn to put some of the same features
on our robots, but for different reasons.
We should build robots with as few
actuated degrees of freedom as possible
because of specific force and
specific power reasons.
Additionally, tails can be helpful for our
bipeds to control the body orientation,
which is often difficult
with underactuated bipeds.