Now we've learned how to think
about a monoped, i.e slipped,
how can we use this knowledge to
control our robot with multiple legs?
In this segment and the two following,
we'll see a great advantage to taking
a compositional approach to control.
In this section, we'll think about
a multi-legged body as really,
well, a composition of
single-legged bodies.
You might come out a little surprised at
just how much can be accomplished from
just a little knowledge
of monoped control.
First, we have to introduce the concept
of a virtual leg, I'll put Raibert here.
Forces and torques exerted on the body
by the set of physical legs and
by the virtual leg are the same.
Here's a pictorial example
where a body with two legs
has the two legs tied together,
not literally but maybe through control,
such that the behavior of the body's
the same as the single leg.
How do we go about
implementing virtual legs?
We have to first think about controlling
the legs within the group i.e,
the legs with the loop of wire
around them in this picture.
The first thing we have to think about
is positioning the toe in flight for
the virtual leg.
This involves positioning
multiple toes for
the physical legs such that the virtual
toe is at the right position.
The second thing we have to think about
is touchdown synchronization to make sure
that all of the physical legs within
a group touch down at the same time, ie,
the time that the vertical
leg touches down.
And lastly, we have to think about
positioning the virtual hip.
You can see that the virtual hip is
somewhere between the physical hips
in the picture above.
And we can actually control the location
of the virtual hip by controlling
the internal forces exerted by the
physical hips, as well as differential,
axial leg forces.
Lastly, I'll point out that behavior,
which we'll see lots of examples of,
is actually just simply a monoped
using this virtual legs idea.
You cannot just have virtual monopeds,
we can also have virtual bipeds.
Here's a picture, again,
from Raibert's book, where we see
examples of a bunch of virtual bipeds.
And with virtual bipeds,
legs operate in pairs, but essentially,
they're one-foot gates.
What this means is that
the control action is mirrored and
repeated from one step to the next.
All of the gates in this pictorial example
are found in horses, for instance.
A chart is a virtual biped where
the virtual hips are located at
the center of mass.
In a piece, the virtual hips are located
close to each other, but on the lateral,
the opposite sides of the body.
Whereas in the bound,
the hips are far apart from each other and
there's a pronounced pitching of the body.
We can control the virtual hip location
and choose between these different gaits
by using some of the methods that I
talked about in the previous slide.
Here's an example of our very own
minitaur implementing a bounding gait.
I'll put out that each hip of minitaur
in this video just thinks of itself as
a vertical hopper.
The front has no knowledge of the back and
the back has no knowledge of the front.
Remember for a bound as we
talk about in previous slide,
we would like the phases of the vertical
hoppers to be asynchronized,
out of phase, this particular phase offset
is actually passively stable because
of the body dynamics.
We'll see a more active control of
the phase offset in the next segment.
I'll point out here that the bound looks
more natural at higher speeds than
the lower speeds since animals
tend to bound at higher speeds.
At slower speeds, they tend to walk.
To summarize, multi-legged robots can be
controlled as compositions of monopeds.
Virtual legs allow you to think of
multiple legs as a single virtual leg and
coordinate them accordingly.
A virtual biped with
a leg-to-leg symmetric control
is actually just a composition
of identical monopeds, and
phase coordination can be
either passive as we saw for
the bound in this segment or it can be
activ as we'll see in the next segment.