Now that we've had a first look at
how compositions can be useful,
the second benefit is the ability to
reuse compositions across bodies.
After all, the template controllers
that we saw for slip in section
4.2 are simple enough that they should
be useful from multiple bodies.
There's usually no problem in implementing
them with the available actuators
in different types of robots.
And so in this section,
we'll try to do that.
We'll assume also the ability to embed the
template without worrying too much about
available actuators or verification.
Here's a video of Jerboa
hopping in the plain.
What we've done here,
is taken the vertical hopping that
we saw in the previous segment and
added in a stepping controller
to position the toe in flight.
The vertical hopping is energized by
the tail, which is specific to the Jerboa.
In addition, I'll point out here,
that the large carbon fiber tube in the
foreground of this video is called a boom.
And what it's doing here, is it's
constraining additional degrees of freedom
of the robot, think of it as
training wheels for the robot.
Before we're ready to control all of
the degrees of freedom of the robot,
we constrain some of them and
test out our controllers.
Here the boom is constraining
the pitch of the robot,
as well as restricting
it to the sagittal pane.
The next segment will allow the pitch
to roam free and see what happens.
We can also use the same idea where
the virtual legs on Minitaur.
Jerboa was a monoped but
Minitaur has multiple legs.
But what we're going to do is coordinate
two of the legs as if they are one,
as we saw in the previous segment.
The virtual leg control ends up being
actually identical to Jerboa, which is
a little surprising but is really showing
off the power of parallel composition.
The within group control ends up
controlling the pitch of the body.
The differential axial leg forces ends
up being a virtual hip torque, and
we can just use the Raibert pitch rolling
idea to control the pitch of the body.
Here's a video of Minitaur pronking.
It's similar to the bounding
in a lot of ways,
except we've added this
pitch coordination.
We're able to get this behavior in a day
or two, while working on the bounding and
this goes to show the power of
reuse from compositionally.
Now that I've shown you our hasty
efforts of getting mentor ranking.
Here's what an African
springbok looks like.
I'm showing you this because firstly, it's
good to be a little in awe of animals.
It just goes to show what steps we have to
take to catch up both technologically and
conceptually.
Secondly, this behavior is extremely and
energetically inefficient.
The spring box use it to either confuse
predators or it's just show off.
Neither which are really
applicable to the robot.
Remember, that we like Bioinspiration but
we're not trying to do biomimicry.
To summarize a lot of what we just saw,
I'll point out that we're not the first
researchers to implement vertical hopping.
Here's Raibert's vertical
hopper from the 1980s.
Here's Jerboa, using his tail to
hop up and down in 2014 or 15.
His Minitaur, using it's virtual
legs to hop up and down.
And here's another robot we have in
the lab called the delta hopper,
which is a three legged freedom
special hopper hoping up and down.
It seems sensible that we should be able
to reuse some of our control ideas across
this vastly different bodies.
After all, biomechanists and
roboticists agree, that the slip model, or
just a mass on a spring, is a good enough
explanation for a lot of animal behaviors.
This idea of reuse is one of
the most important advantages
of a compositional way of
constructing controllers.
The next immediate benefit is that
having a library of templates and
template controllers automatically
suggests new combinations of them.
In this light, I'll describe two
combinations which create a new behaviors
which were useful for Minitaur.
Say we have a library of these three
controllers of vertical hopping.
A rimless wheel and a pitch control.
By using the pitch control
primitive in the horizontal plane,
we can actually get Minitaur to turn,
something that is not immediately
obvious because Minitaur only
has sagittal plane activation.
Additionally, by using the pitch
control idea in the roll direction, and
by changing the roll offset from zero.
We can get it to do this crabbing behavior
laterally, which is really unusual and
surprising.
I'm actually going to leave the most
visually appealing of these
generative combinations till
the next segment, leaping.
These ideas of reusing in generating,
might remind you of something we're all
very familiar with, spoken language.
After all, if I have a new thought,
I'm usually able to find the words
that I've learned previously
to describe it, usually.
This is not a coincidental connection.
It's happened for
computer science, in fact,
which is why there are numerous
programming languages that let computer
programmers express themselves
from simple primitives.
And a language for programming work,
or robots, is indeed something for
roboticists to strive towards.
So let's take stock of where
compositional techniques lie.
I've made a crude table here, where
Compositional techniques are on the right.
And for lack of a better term,
the Holistic techniques,
where you must model the whole robot,
and generate a controller for
all of the degrees of freedom
at once are on the left.
The first thing roboticists care
about is stability guarantees.
We'd really like to know
that our behavior is stable.
For holistic techniques,
there are several methods that you
could look up in the literature.
For compositional controllers, we could
use some of the same techniques but
what we'd really like to do,
is be able to leverage
templates stability properties
which are much simpler to analyze.
And somehow, be able to guarantee that
the body is stable under composition.
We haven't figure this how yet,
but there's been some progress.
Second point is Underactuation,
where we'd like a few actuators to
control many degrees and freedom.
There are a few holistic techniques.
For instance, if you had a linear
controllable system you could use a linear
quadratic regulator to generate
control inputs for you,
that would control all of
your degrees of freedom.
However, techniques like this would
require very good models which are often
hard to get.
In contrary, for compositional techniques,
if the template isn't actuated like we
want, there's very little we can do.
We'll see in the next
section how we leverage
body coupling to channel one
actuator into different templates.
The third point is Optimality guarantees.
Optimal control,
lets us think about this in a principled
way with holistic techniques.
However, in the compositional domain,
we're actively restricting the set
of controllers we can use, and
hence, we can't really have
these guarantees anymore.
Given these tradeoffs,
what are some of the benefits we
have from compositional techniques?
In terms of modelling and
calibration, most of the holistic
methods must be quite precise.
However, the compositional techniques
can survive with much cruder models.
After all the templates plans are only
crude representations of our bodies and
the template controllers are chosen for
their large ability basins.
Next, the controller synthesis for
compositional techniques is very easy.
Because each template can be thought of
as a single input single output system,
making the number of parameters
to think about much smaller.
However, in the holistic setting
the number of parameters for
this n input n output system
might be quite large.
It often goes exponentially, and
the number of parameters you have to think
about, when developing the controller,
is very large.
Lastly, the ability to reuse and generate
controllers, which we just talked about in
the previous slides, is one of the best
selling points of compositional control.
To summarize, a compositional approach to
synthesis allows us to reuse templates
that we've learned already
on different robots.
As well as to generate new behaviors
that we might not have even thought of.