Last segment we looked at
reusing templates on bodies.
There's another facet of composition
that's useful even with a single body.
Sometimes there are different ways
to anchor the same templates.
Since the bodies are coupled,
a single actuator output may
affect many degrees of freedom and
we have some flexibility of choosing how
the actuator controls a degree of freedom.
For this section we need to
introduce a new template.
We've already seen pitch control for
as well as for Jerboa.
So, let's remember how that works.
Let's say we have an actuator which
could be a virtual hip torque or
a physical hip torque or anything else.
And we have an attitude degree of
freedom which is essentially an angle.
And what we do is we choose
the torque to be a PD controller or
similar servo on the angle
that we're trying to control.
Now we introduce a new template which
is called tailed reorientation.
Bodies with a tail have this
internal shape angle which
you can find out more
about from this paper.
And what we can do is allow the tail to
work and affect the internal shape angle,
to reorient the body.
Let's take SLIP on Jerboa from the
previous segment, and now remove the boom,
which was locking the body pitch.
What we're going to do is let the hip
torque control the body pitch and
stance, and the tail torque
control the shape angle in flight.
This is what that looks like.
Empirical work is really in progress.
And some of the reasons why
these experiments are difficult
are that you need very
good orientation sensing.
These experiments are also sensitive to
the location of the center of mass which
is why I have to have this unicorn horn to
move the center of mass further forward.
Essentially what we've done is
we've extended Raibert's ideas
from his original three degree of freedom
planar hopper to this much more coupled,
four degree of freedom tailed system.
So is that the only way
to get your robot to hop?
Well let's see, the answer is no.
Here's an example that
just borrows Rex's idea
of having the hip energize
a SLIP like behavior.
The C legs in this video are here
primarily because we could not get enough
traction with the point legs.
But we don't really thinks that that's
that important for the behavior.
So the hips control the slip
degrees of freedom and
the tail then needs to control the body
angle as well as the shape angle.
This video shows one way in which the tail
can control attitude degrees of freedom
by interacting with the ground.
You'll remember from section 3.2
by using tails to interact with
the ground is not unusual
even in the animal kingdom.
Okay, so
we have two ways that Jerboa could hop.
The two ways have important differences.
The hip energized hopping is faster.
It actually goes seven to
eight body lengths per second.
But, the tail energized
hopping needs less traction,
which could be important if you're
trying to hop on the slippery surface.
Additionally, they impose different
morphological constraints.
We haven't spoken about this before,
but when we anchor templates,
there is a push forward of
controllers from template to body.
But complimentary to this to use
the template controllers we need to
pull back some of the body's parameters.
This is a topic of active research as you
can see from the reference in this slide.
But this morphological
reduction imposes constraints
on the allowable parameter
space of the body.
In this instance, the hip/g-energized
hopping seems to prefer
a different location for the center of
mass than the tail-energized hopping.
To summarize, having alternate
solutions is a good thing.
What we've done is we've shown you two
ways that Jerboa can hop in the plane.
And the different environmental conditions
might make us prefer one solution
over the other.