So far, we have been looking
at steady state behaviors,
which means that the energy of
the robot changes slowly, if at all.
This last segment of the course,
we'll look at leaping.
Leaping really involves
rapid changes in energy.
And that brings in very different
techniques that we need for analysis.
Here are two videos of Jerboa.
On the left it's doing the hopping
we saw on the previous segment, and
on the right it's doing a leaping behavior
to try and get on top of this box.
Which would you guess is
the easier behavior to analyze?
The answer is, by far,
the one on the left.
The behavior on the right is
called transitional behavior.
And the analytical difficulty with that
is that it can't be encoded in terms of
basins and generalized energy,
like we showed in section 4.1.
However, it's not always so bad.
Here's a video of me rolling a ball
on a table and a makeshift corner.
The ball has one or more impacts
with the boxes on the sides, and for
the most part,
bounces away from the corner.
This deceptively simple demonstration
exposes some of the nasty underbelly
of hybrid systems, though.
Notice that for the concave corner, even
though the initial velocity is variable,
the final velocity is relatively
stable to perturbations.
However, in the convex corner,
the opposite is true.
Even small variations in initial velocity
cause the ball to diverge completely
into different final velocities.
So the first concave corner results
in a convergent transition,
whereas in the second case,
we get a divergent one.
The first example where this is relevant
is a pronking leap for Minitaur,
as you can see in these videos.
Through our virtual leg coordination
anchoring effort, we can try and
ensure that the multiple legs
touch down at the same time.
But in practice they all touch down
at slightly different times, but
the advantage is that these
impacts are usually convergent.
You can try this at home by
picking up a chair or a table and
lightly dropping it about
one inch off the ground.
And you can see that the final condition
is relatively independent of how you drop
the chair.
The same is true of Minitaur.
And a lot of the time we can ignore
the variability of how it lands and
instead focus on composing the behavior
using sequential parallel composition
that we learned about before.
All of these are just the bounding and
pronking that we've seen
in the previous segments.
With added vertical energy for one stride.
The vertical leap is about two and half
times MInitaur's normal standing height.
You might be thinking, my cat can
jump higher than that, probably true.
In an absolute height you could
probably jump higher than that as well.
But try without bending your knees or
your ankle.
You might see that it's extremely
hard to jump without knees.
RHex and Jerboa are two robots that
don't have any active knees or
ankles, that is,
it can't actively extend its leg.
We've been able to make RHex and
Jerboa perform leaping behaviors as well.
Using their legs and
body together to go through a sequence of
hybrid transitions before going airborne.
I've shown you a brief set of samples
here where you can look up RHex and
Jerboa leaping on YouTube to
see a more full selection of
the leaps possible on this way.
To manage the exploding complexity of
the hybrid transitions, Aaron Johnson
came up with this object called
the ground reaction complex, or GRC.
The GRC is really a mathematical structure
for bookkeeping the hybrid transitions.
Here's an example of a GRC for
a planar, one legged robot.
This is actually what you'd get if
you removed the tail from Jerboa.
In each cartoon,
the cyan dot represents an active contact,
and the magenta dots
represent inactive contacts.
And maybe you can see how
the GRC is constructed.
The most surprising thing we found is
that when given a similar leap command,
in certain ranges, RHex and
Jerboa produce very similar leaps,
as you can see in this image.
The question then,
obviously, is why, and when.
The answer to this question is not easy,
and is a topic of active research.
But for now, we suspect the answer has
to do with ranges of conditions when,
to refer back to my earlier demonstration,
the ball rolls into a concave
angle versus a convex angle.
In this image, each data point is
the apex state of a leap made by RHex
on the left and Jerboa on the right.
And you can see that there
are regions of leap commands which
produced very similar trends
in the final apex state.
As I mentioned before, analyzing why
is still the topic of active research.
To summarize, transitions go
through various hybrid modes,
which makes them difficult to
analyze with energy basins.
Some transitions are nicer than others,
though.
Minitaur leaps fall in the nice category,
and the leaps can mostly be
implemented and analyzed using
parallel and sequential composition.
RHex and Jerboa leaps, on the other hand,
are much more difficult to analyze, and
we're beginning to do so
using the ground reaction complex.