Why and how do we move?
Well, we're animals.
Why do animals move?
Animals, the very word means movement.
Breathing, Animalia has to
do with things that breathe.
Aristotle, thousands of years ago,
thought about such questions and
asked why it is that animals move.
And he understood that there was
some combination of reason and
motivation and perception.
And curiously, he didn't have much
to say about the motor act itself.
So, for thousands of years,
we've been thinking about such questions.
And recently, the biologists have
gotten together many different
fields within biology and a new discipline
of movement ecology has developed.
And the movement ecologists
have come to understand that
we need to think about many
scales at the same time.
We need to think about limbs over seconds.
We need to think about
bodies over minutes.
We need to think about places that
the animals travel over days.
And of course over continents,
there are migrations and yearly motion.
The basic components of study involve
motion science as the engineers
understand it, navigation as
the cognitive scientists understand it,
natural sciences as the physicists and
chemists participate,
and many, many,
many branches come together.
In our module, we're not going to so
much consider the environmental
record of travel.
We're not so much going to consider
the motivation and evolutionary drivers.
We're going to focus largely on the
mechanical and navigational capabilities.
And when we think about the connections
to biology, we're trying very,
very hard to understand the lessons
of evolutionary ecology.
But mostly we'll be focused on what
the people in biomechanics and
the neuroscientists and
the cognitive scientists can tell us.
So welcome to this special
inquiry into mobility.
We'll be spending a lot of time
thinking about the relationship
between animal mobility and
machine mobility in the hours to come.
Well, how do animals move?
It starts with Newton.
Newton says, F equals m a.
The body accelerates consequent
upon forces applied to it.
The forces of reaction against
the environment cause accelerations.
And those forces are carried
by appendages, limbs, tails.
We'll be concerned with the way
in which the appendages
of the animals or
the machines carry the forces and
imbue the body with reaction
forces from the ground.
This begins a very long and
very much unfinished story, because the
appendages have to travel with the body.
And so
the appendages can't be left behind, and
if they're going to be
asserting forces and
transmitting forces from the ground
to the body, they have to oscillate.
If they oscillate, they have to
oscillate in tight coordination.
And tight coordination requires very
complicated and intricate feedback
loops such as the biologists are beginning
to uncover and understand, but
we in engineering have been thinking
about for a very, very long time.
The feedback loops include pathways
from the environment through the limbs,
from the environment through the nerves,
within the body,
through the limbs and nerves, and
all of this pathways are mixed.
What's particularly fascinating to
us in robotics about animal movement
is that the animals have a lot of their
intelligence built into their bodies.
Their bodies mix form with function
in a marvelous and confusing way.
Muscles.
Muscles in the animals
sometimes function as motors,
sometimes they function as brakes,
sometimes they function as springs.
Intelligence.
The intelligence is baked into the body.
Well, how don't the animals move?
And why are we spending all
of our time on the animals?
The animals inspire this course because
they have been moving successfully for
hundreds of millions of years.
Animals invented limbed mobility, and
we would like to try to be inspired and
to learn from their mobility.
The animals are focused
on body-based sensing.
And traditionally, this has been less true
of the engineering artifacts in robotics,
it's very hard for
us to build sensors and actuators
all into the same body and into the limbs
that will be interacting with the world.
How do the animals move?
Well, on land, they stride.
How don't they move?
Don't they have wheels?
Why don't the animals have wheels?
Biology has invented wheels a few times
in the form of molecular motors and
sometimes in the form of organisms.
Here's a marvelous stomatopod
called the mantis shrimp.
This stomatopod was
investigated 20 years ago,
25 years ago by my good friend and
colleague, Bob Full and his collaborators.
And what they discovered was
that this animal rolls itself up
into a ball, really, into a disk.
And it rolls along the beach
as a disk-like wheel.
But there are very, very,
very few animals that move in this manner.
How about in liquid?
How do animals move in liquid?
In liquid, they slither or they swim.
They don't have jets?
Well, sure, they have jets.
Scientists, biologists have been
looking at squids for decades and
trying to understand the nature
of the jet propulsion that
allows the squids to
whish through the seas.
They think of the squids
as just hearts set free.
But jet propulsion turns out to be very,
very inefficient.
It's very inefficient to
contain the reaction mass.
Mostly, when animals move,
they use their limbs.
They use their fins, they use their legs,
they use their tails.
This course is going to be focused on the
relationship between the inspiration we
receive from biology and the engineering
that we can build in consequence.
We therefore will be
studying limbed mobility.
And again, when I say limbed,
I will mean all sorts of limbs,
all sorts of appendages, tails and
arms and legs and possibly even fingers.
We will be inspired, but we will not copy.
The first lessons that we learn from our
friends in biology is that the history of
animal form is very complicated.
Millions of years of history that
we only partially understand.
Let's take for example tails.
What are tails used for?
Well, here's a beautiful macaque monkey.
This beautiful macaque monkey has a very
long, bushy tail, and we might be inspired
to try to build such a tail in our
robots until we talk to the biologists,
who tell us that, well, this tail is
mostly used for play-time signalling.
Probably we don't want our robots to
do too much play-time signalling, so
we will probably not build a tail for
this purpose.
How about the beaver?
The beaver has a tail, the beaver
uses its tail for swimming, right?
And we know the beaver uses its tail for
slapping and
warning its fellow beavers
of possible enemies.
These sound like very,
very useful roles for tails.
But really, as it turns out,
when you talk to the biologists,
the beaver's tail is used for storing fat.
We probably don't want to store fat in
our robots, and we probably will be very
careful about how we use insights from
the beaver tail in building our robots.
And then there are all the many
animals such as pigs or
humans that have vestigial tails.
Do we really want to build
a vestigial tail on our robots?
Probably not.
We would like to work with principles and
not appearances.
We have spent a lot of time
talking with Bob Full and
his students about how the lizards
use their tails to right themselves
in situations of crisis or imbalance.
And we've spent a number of years
working together with him and
his students to build tailed robots that
don't look anything like those lizards,
but have tails that function a little
bit like the lizard's in their
self-righting ability, as seen by this
little robot car on the left hand.
And seen by our Rex robot
running across the pedestal
of Ben Franklin and righting itself with
its tail when it falls off the cliff.
These robots don't look anything like
the lizard, but the principles Involved
in getting the body level in consequence
of the tail motion is exactly
the kind of thing that we want to learn
how to do and generalize in robotics.
So we're concerned with bioinspiration and
not mimicry.