Bio-inspiration.
Wait a minute!
Don't machines already move better?
Machines, they're great.
We've been building machines for
hundreds of years.
We have the fastest machine that's
ever traveled, we have Helios 2.
NASA built Helios 2 to
study solar properties.
And Helios 2 in its fastest ascent
toward the Sun reached a speed of
0.22 kilometers per second, which is
fractionally like the speed of light.
The speed of light is faster than
anything in the universe can travel.
We have faster machines than anything
that biology has come up with.
And how about capacity?
Our machines have far greater loads
than any animal could possibly bear.
Our largest cargo ship, the MSC Oscar,
carries 200,000 cubic meters of space.
And you can see how it dwarfs
the human being in the picture here.
But if we move away from mere speed,
and mere load,
and mere speed overload and
study a little bit more carefully.
We begin to see that the animals
are marvelously better sources of
mobility than anything we've yet
been able to come up with in engineering.
I'm plotting a graph that my colleague,
Professor Art Kuo at University of
Michigan has added to, where he displays
the cost of transport which you could
think about as miles per gallon really
in this chart, it's gallons per mile.
And the way you'd like
to start thinking about
cost of transport is a notion
called specific resistance.
Specific resistance measures
the energy expended
to achieve a certain distance
with a certain load.
Or, you can think about
specific resistance
as the time average of
the amount of power expended
to achieve a speed while
carrying a certain mass.
You can see from the charts that
the animals, if you disregard their load,
are far more cost efficient,
have much lower
specific resistance than any of the
machines that we've been able to build.
And it's only when we begin to think about
the cost of transport including load,
that the machines begin to be competitive.
Agility, there's no question.
The animals are far more agile than
anything we've been able to build.
You think your Porsche accelerates nicely.
The Porsche accelerates from zero to
100 kilometers per hour in two seconds.
That's about two meters
per second per second.
The sailfish in the ocean,
when it's hunting, accelerates at
eight meters per second per
second at nearly the same speeds.
And the cheetah, when it travels
at about 60 kilometers per hour,
is accelerating at least 13
meters per second squared.
So the animals are an order of magnitude
more agile if we measure
agility by acceleration.
We'll be spending some amount of
time in this course thinking about
metrics of mobility such
as specific resistance.
Perhaps we'll talk about agility measures.
And by almost any of these measures,
the animals are far,
far better than any machine that we've yet
been able to build.
And so it behooves us to think
about what the animals know and
to teach us concerning mobility.
There's a completely independent and
marvelous reason to think about
animals in the context of mobility.
Because evolution teaches us that
mobility is actually the very origin
of intelligence.
Way back in the Precambrian
era there was a shift
from primitive animals
that were filter feeders,
just passing the water through their
gills, their gill equivalents.
So they were animals in the sense
of Animalia, they were breathers,
they were movers but
they weren't that mobile as bodies.
There was a marvelous shift
around between 500 million and
300 million years ago from mere filter
feeding to selective predation.
Where the animals began to
direct themselves toward other
animals so as to consume
those big packages of energy.
And some of the other
animals began to develop
escape mechanisms to remove
themselves from this predation.
And, it's been known for about 30 years
in biology, evolutionary biology now,
that this is the origin
of the neural crest and
the origin of the vertebrates and
therefore the origin of our brain.
It's the mobile seeking
brains that develop.
The mammalian hippocampus is the prime
of example of a seeking brain and
the intelligence that it confers.
The 2014 Nobel Prize was
given to the Mosers,
an amazing married pair of
neuroscientists in Norway,
who discovered that animals have maps.
It was known that animals had
some kind of mapping capability.
But, the the anatomy of the maps,
the seat of spacial navigation was unknown
until they showed, the Mosers did,
that animals have grid cells
that respond to relative
position and play cells that
respond to landmarks in the world.
And increasing work by cognitive
scientists and animal cognition
experts begins to reveal that
the origin of episodic memory,
our own sense of who we are, and where
we've been, and how we've come to be,
is deeply, deeply rooted in
this hippocampic structure.
It's not just the mammals
that have seeking brains,
although our seeking brains are
particularly well developed and advanced.
It seems to be every animal that's mobile.
Most animals that are mobile
develop a general cognitive map and
these maps hypothetically
arose from olfactory trackers.
Meaning long, long, long ago before
animals had very much of a nervous system
they had what's called chemotaxis.
They had the ability to sniff out
different concentrations of different
molecular substances.
Many, many different animals
have been shown to use
smell in conjunction
with their locomotion and
their navigation honey bees,
deep water sharks, homing pigeons.
It seems that in those animals that
are seekers, they seek after prey or they
seek after scarce fauna, they have larger
structures where the neuroanatomists
have found the structures,
the seat of their cognitive max.
They have larger structures,
they have larger brains if they're
involved in competitive navigation.
This competitive navigation arose 500
million years ago, and it was built
from chemotaxis, the primitive ability to
distinguish different molecular species
from each other, so that one would not
eat the poison and instead seek the food.
These notions of navigation
built on chemotaxis
have generated many intriguing
theories on the part of the cognitive
science of evolutionary biologist that
help us think about how to organize
navigation in robots between gradient
based or smell strengthening basis.
As distinct from landmark based or
topological navigation.
And so this is a marvelous conversation
between cognitive scientists and
roboticists that emerges
at the fulcrum of mobility.
We will spend much less of our
time in this course thinking about
the navigational capacities
of the cognitive maps.
But those questions and
those excitements will be there for
the whole lectures and you will see
them cropping up from time to time
as we talk about the mechanical
bases of mobility.