Well, we are going to be focusing,
particularly, on legged mobility.
And legged mobility brings us
to an understanding of and
engagement with dynamics and
the management of energy.
Why focus on legs?
Well, we're humans and we're particularly
interested in human animals.
And humans live and work largely on land.
Look at this very, very interesting map
produced about 20 years ago by
some economists at Harvard.
They show you the density
of the navigable and
temperate earth ecozones
which comprise only
8% of the inhabitable landmass on earth.
But this 8% accounts for
50% of the world's economic output.
And so we see that despite our wonderful
legs and our wonderful mobility,
the largest component of human living and
working is happening on a tiny,
tiny substrate,
8% of the inhabited landmass.
And we suspect, as the economists predict,
that as human beings come to
be able to exploit more of this inhabited
land mass with greater mobility engines.
That there will be much,
much greater economic output in presently
underserved and economically
deprived regions of the planet.
We're also interested in legs because
there are a variety of inhospitable
environments where people can't go, or
shouldn't go, that legs are crucial.
For example, about ten years ago, there
was a terrible disaster at Sago Mine.
And it was clear from the news reports and
careful formal studies of the accident
site that if we'd had better robots
that were more mobile, more easily
able to traverse these very non level.
No roads here, no flat fields here.
If we had robots that were able to
traverse these very difficult, broken,
unstable land regimes, we possibly could
have done better by the disaster victims.
Not just on Earth are we interested
in terrestrial mobility,
there's extraterrestrial mobility.
It's not that you can't roam
around Mars with wheels.
The amazing Mars Rovers have way, way,
way outlived their planned life, but
they were limited in their mobility.
Dramatically limited by their wheels so
that the Mars Rover Spirit
got stuck in the sand.
And ten years ago it died in the Martian
winter because it couldn't free itself
from the sand trap.
We think in robotics that legs
are better than wheels and
legs are better than tracks.
And legs and tails and
appendages are better than jets.
Why do we think that?
We find, when we look carefully,
that legs and
appendages enable
the mobile agent to direct
the ground reaction forces that we
talked about in the previous segment.
We can direct the ground reaction
forces and by directing them we can
choose to either leap forward,
for example,
as Aaron Johnson's Rex Robot is
doing in this slowed down movie.
Or we can redirect them to jump up,
as Aaron Johnson's same Rex Robot
is doing in this different movie.
Where very,
very minute differences in the timing, and
the forces, and
the coordination of the leg patterns
give rise to dramatically
different ground reaction forces.
And those very different ground reaction
forces achieve totally different
kinds of mobility.
Never with a tracked or a wheeled vehicle
would one be able to achieve these sorts
of navigational and mobile feats
that the animals take for granted.
Another very, very important use for
legged mobility is
the possibility of feeling
the substrate through our limbs.
This is called proprioception, and this
movie of Rex trudging its way up a slope.
We want the machine to stop midway and
park itself in such a fashion
that it doesn't, any longer, need to exert
any current, any torque against the world.
So that it could stay there for
a long time without burning up energy.
To do so it must feel the forces of
the ground through its legs, in its hip.
And by feeling them, it can balance and
achieve an efficient stand.
So in this course we will be spending
most of our time on legged mobility and
all of our time on appendaged mobility,
tails and legs.
As soon as we say that,
we're bound to consider the fundamental
physical properties before we take
on any further considerations.
Mobility starts with physics.
Mobility starts with Newton, F = ma.
Mobility requires
an understanding of Lagrange's
reformulation of Newton's
laws into a principle
of least action that gave
him a mechanics that began
to seem more geometric and
less analytical.
We will visit Lagrange's
reformulation of Newton's laws and
we will make major use of his ideas.
Most importantly, Hamilton came along and
understood that these least action
principles could be again reconceived in
terms of conservation principles,
energy conservation, energy loss.
In this course,
we're concerned with losing energy,
we don't want to conserve energy.
We want to expend the joules
in our batteries and
get those joules into the body in
the form of kinetic energy of the body,
so that the body can move around and
get things done for the robot.
In order to do so, we must waste energy,
we must spend our energy
on directed motion and
on thermal loss and other losses.
We'll be spending a lot of
time thinking about energy and
energy based methodologies in this course.
So mobility starts with physics but
it takes a very long and important detour
through technology, whose fundamentals
are still not completely understood.
We're very, very much concerned with
scarce resources such as specific force.
Specific force means force per mass, why?
Well, we must apply
the ground reaction forces in
adequate magnitude to achieve our end.
To do so,
with electro-mechanical actuators which
are the cleanest and the fastest acting.
We engage in the history of
recent material science and
magnetism, which is an ongoing,
slowly developing, very important area.
The progression of energetic
density in rare earth
magnets has made a slow
change in the capacity of our
motors to impart forces
without requiring large,
large, large rotors and stators.
And so, we show you here
a picture of an Maxon motor,
which until recently had been one of
the preferred engines of our robots.
In recent years,
it’s become clear that more than just
the materials properties
of the motors are crucial.
We know that their ability to shed
thermal load, their ability to shed heat,
the wasted energy that gets burned up in
joule heating in their wires is very,
very important.
And recently some of our colleagues,
Professor Sangbae Kim at MIT,
have pointed out that the air gap
radius when it gets enlarged for
the same mass, gives much,
much greater torque.
And so we should be thinking about
motors that have good rare earth magnets
in them and motors that have good
thermal shedding capability in them.
And motors that are built with large air
gap radii as shown in Sangbae's picture.
This confusion, interesting confusion,
combination of fundamental materials,
properties and technological, commercial
off the shelf availabilities is one of
the many wonderful confusing aspects
of robotics right now in its infancy.
And some day we'll get
to the bottom of it.
But for now,
what we know is we want greater specific
force than we can get in our machines.
Another scarce resource is traction.
Traction in the claws of the cheetah
that we'll come back to and
talk about subsequently.
The cheetah in the former
pictures was able to achieve its
huge accelerations as you saw
on those pictures because it has
claws that can engage the ground and
form virtual pin joints.
None of our robots has the ability to
recruit such huge traction forces.
And so, for us in the robotics world,
trying to achieve those accelerations
even if we had the forces
would cause us to be skittering over
that grass as if it were ice or Teflon.
Another scarce resource is power.
Power is the rate at which I
can move my joules around,
the rate at which energy gets
transferred from one form or another.
Another way to think about power is
the speed at which I can sustain my force.
Specific power, of course,
means power per mass.
And I want to get as great power per mass
as I can out of my actuator technology.
Here is an example of one our more recent
vertical climbing robots in a paper by Dr.
Goran Lynch and Professor Clark
now at Florida State University,
Professor Pei-Chun Lin now at
National Taiwan University, and myself.
This wall running robot was achieved
by introducing compliant elements
that could absorb the energy
from the motor whilst the legs were
retracting so as to spread out
the time over which the energy had to be
moved and avoid burning the motor coils.
This is another example of
a technological consideration
that must have formal foundations
that we don't understand yet.
But we will be coming back to these
considerations in the segment
two of the course.
Mobility starts with physics,
it takes a detour through technology,
it ends with the hope of programming work.
What might that mean?
As we'll see through
the hours of lectures,
our robots start with architectures,
the architectures of computers and
the architectures of motors and
the architectures of sensors.
There are hardware elements of various
kinds, and each of these hardware elements
has its own interesting story,
mix of technological accident and
fundamental material science, or
fundamental physical principles.
Each of these components that go into
the architecture that makes a machine
has its own fascinating story.
At the end, we build up our actuators and
our actuators communicate information
about the state of the environment, the
state of the body, the state of the limbs.
All the way back to the communicating and
coordinating structures and
the intelligence.
But at the end of the day, these
coordination patterns must be used to
achieve some kind of
stable energetic display,
some kind of stable energetic shedding.
And we will come to call these basins.
Basins of attraction,
places where energy wants to go low,
energy wants to get shed and
the world and the robot,
when they shake hands, wants to
end up in these low energy states.
These basins become symbols and
the symbols begin to be composable.
When we have symbols that are composable,
we are on the threshold
of programming languages.
And so the last week of this course
will be concerned with our ability to
compose these basins, these symbols,
these energy basins and
build more complicated behaviors from old.
For example,
if we think about a language of work, if
we think about basins as symbols,
we want to translate the abstract goals.
Move your body here, or move that dish
from this shelf into that refrigerator.
We want to translate these goals
into sensor-torque strategies.
And so we want to take our
architectures as they're connected
up to the world through our limbs and
we want to build basins.
Here's an example of Dr.
Rob Burridge's thesis from 1992,
wherein he and Al Rizzi showed
how to build a juggling basin.
Here the energetic design is for
an oscillating vertical
motion of the ping pong ball.
The ping pong ball wants to lie
down at that vertical motion,
and when we try to knock that ball away,
the basin restores the ball down
to the low energy goal state.
Here's Burridge's work on sequential
composition of those basins and
we won't talk very much
about this technically now.
We'll do this in week four.
But you would like to think about
these sequential compositions as
the beginning of a programming
language for work.
The virtue of formal programming
languages is that they're amenable to
mathematical proofs.
The virtue of mathematical proofs is that
they sometimes give rise to predictable
results.
It's not that the proof means
that the robot will work.
The proof gives you a debugging tool.
Because if the theorem is correct, and
the behavior does not work
in the physical world,
then you know that the hypothesis
underlying that theorem doesn't hold.
And it helps you in your debugging step.
We don't like to think about robots
that don't have formal properties.
We don't like to think about
computers that crash, but
we're willing to live with them
if they're on our desktop.
If those computers are running our
elevator, or running our jet, or running
our search and rescue equipment, we
really, really don't want them to crash.
And we would like to have
formal mathematical principles
that preclude such possibilities.
These are the themes that we will
be covering in the weeks and
segments to come.
Welcome to our special mobility course
at the University of Pennsylvania,
Penn GRASP Laboratory.