[MUSIC]
Welcome to week two of our robotics
special course on mobility.
This week, we'll be focused on
the components of mobile robots.
The components fall into two
major conceptual pieces.
First, we want to introduce behavioral
components that we'll call templates.
What's a template?
A template, as an example, is a so
called compass gait, what is that?
Think about a wheel rolling down a hill,
think about a spoked wheel
rolling down the hill,
take the rim of that wheel off and
think about wheel rolling down the hill.
Now take those spokes and think about
their transition from one point,
to the other point, to the other point.
Remove all but two of those spokes,
and let those two spokes oscillate and
suddenly, we've got a compass gait.
That's a very, very,
very simple mechanical system.
Still pretty complicated to understand but
simple enough that we can
understand it pretty thoroughly.
And that dynamical system will turn out
the be the organizing principle for
many, many quasi-static gaits.
That's a compass gait, it's a template.
Another template is the spring
loaded inverted pendulum.
This is the template for running.
Think about this as the pogo stick.
The pogo stick is even harder to
understand than the compass gait but
still we can understand it pretty well.
It's the organizing principle for almost
all animal running that we know of and
the organizing principle for
all good running robots that
have been built to date.
Here is the origin of
the spring loaded inverted
pendulum in robotics introduced by Dr.
Marc Raibert,
then a professor at MIT in 1983,
when he first showed us how to think
about dynamical management of
mobility via energy control.
We'll spend a little bit of time
talking about Raibert's wonderful work
which informs much of what's
gone in legged robotics for
the last 30 years since that time.
The second half hour of our week two
will be concerned not with behavioral
components but with the literal physical
components, the materials properties,
the structures, and the power, as I
promised in the original work on week one.
We're going to be thinking about scaling,
strengths of materials,
how the same weight is not adequate
to support the strength of much,
much larger scaled mechanisms.
We'll be thinking about
the materials properties.
What about the compliance
properties of these materials?
How do these compliance
materials scale with weight?
What compliance properties do we want?
How do we choose those materials?
We'll be thinking about figures
of merit and robustness and
we'll be thinking about how to build novel
materials into novel structures that
have never been built before because
of the revolution in manufacturing
brought about by these
MakerBot style devices.
The last thing that we'll talk
about in this week of the course
will be our actuator technology, the all
important source of force and power.
And the limitations of actuators, and the
possibilities of using actuators as they
are today and actuators as they may
be in the future will comprise one
of the most important
components of this week.
Welcome to week two,
we'll spend all of this week thinking
about the components but don't
be impatient because those components will
turn into robots in week three and four.