[MUSIC]
Welcome to week four,
the last installment of our robotics MOOC.
In this week, we will bring you from what
we understand today about composition of
behavior to the horizons of research.
Where we can begin to achieve behaviors
that we imperfectly understand but
have some hope of understanding
well enough to become truly
compositional as if we have
a language of programing work.
In the first segment,
we'll be thinking about the abstract idea
of dynamical composition, we'll come back
to this ideas of sequential uncomposition,
sequential and
parallel composition that were introduced
in the very original first week and we'll
treat them a little bit more carefully
both from the point of view of
mathematics and of energetic design.
Here's an example of a RHex like hexapod
seen from the side and the sagittal plane,
kinematically behaving just as if
it were the pogo stick on the left.
And here's an instantiated version
of RHex in the physical world,
running through the grass.
Acting on the grass just
as if it were a pogo stick,
even though it doesn't
look anything like one.
You can see in slow motion
when RHex is properly tuned,
it does begin to look like a pogo stick
from the point of view of its mass center.
We'll be talking about
these ideas of anchoring
the templates in the bodies in 4.1.
In 4.2, we'll introduce you to
a family of compositions that we have
been practicing for a while, but
only recently do we begin to think we have
the mathematics to underlie them formally.
We'll start by talking about why
parallel composition is hard.
We'll then discuss the minotaur
robot that you've seen before and
the jerboa robot that you've seen before.
As increasingly complicated
compositions of simple pieces.
You remember the Ray Bird
hopper from before, and
you remember the rimless
wheel from before.
We're going to put these two together
to build a two dimensional hopper, and
then we're going to put them together
with that inertial tail reorienting
style behavior that we showed
you earlier to get the minotaur.
We're going to do the same thing to
the more complicated jerboa body.
And we can begin to get mathematical
proofs of the empirical behaviors that you
see revealed in these videos.
The last segment of this course will bring
you to the horizons of research of what we
understand.
Here, we actually get the minotaur
to bound around in a stable manner
using simple compositions
of vertical Ray Bird
style hoppers in ways that we can
almost begin to prove are correct.
We can use the same compositions
in different bodies.
We can use different
compositions in the same body.
The last piece of this week
will be spent thinking about
the jagged edge of what we understand,
which are these transitional behaviors
such as Aaron Johnson's leaping Rhex.
And Aaron Johnson's scrambling Rhex, where
you can see if we could get this down
right, we would be able to hugely
increase the operating capacity and
the rescue abilities
of machines like Rhex.
Welcome to the final installment of our
mobility component of this robotics MOOC.
In this week four of the mobility effort,
we will be talking about
the beginnings of programing.
What we do and don't understand, and
what sorts of behaviors we can get
in the physical world with what
sorts of mathematical guarantees.