[MUSIC]
Welcome to week three
of our robotics MOOC.
In this week, we'll be thinking about
taking those primitives of week two and
putting together,
attaching limbs to bodies, and
getting them to start to behave.
The first half hour of this week
concerns itself with what limbs can do,
what they can't do, and
how to think about their capabilities,
first of all in motion,
and second of all at work.
What do I mean by that?
In 3.1.1, we'll review kinematics,
which is the study of limbs in motion.
What are the mobility properties of
the limbs without thinking about
how they achieve those motions in time?
Then in the second segment
of this half hour,
we'll review the way in
which Newton's laws,
when they attach to the masses that are
constrained by these complicated linkages,
how those laws create very complicated and
interesting dynamical effects
such as I talked about in the original
discussion of animal mobility.
It will turn out that when animals run,
they turn themselves into pogo sticks.
Remember that slip template from week two?
You're going to see it here in many,
many different incarnations.
In bipeds, in quadrupeds, in six legged
runners, in many legged runners.
You're going to see how the kinematics
of these linkages get transformed into
pogo sticks by the animal coordination
that we try to be inspired about and
build into our robots.
Here is an example of a machine that
doesn't look like the pogo stick, but
it's built to run as
a composition of pogo sticks and
leap like a coordinated single pogo stick.
Stay tuned.
We won't talk about this composition yet.
That's for week four, but
that's where we're headed.
The second half hour of this week will
be concerned with designs of bodies.
How do we attach these wonderful limbs to
bodies to get complicated robots that can
do interesting tasks for us?
We'll start with sprawled posture runners.
Very strongly informed by what
our friends in biomechanics and
integrated biology can tell us
about how the arthropods do it.
Well, many, many, many engineers and
even hobbyist have been inspired
by the sprawled posture of arthropods,
which are the most successful
animals on the planet if you consider
their weight and biomass, but
we'll be focusing on a machine that
doesn't look anything like a cockroach yet
is bio-inspired and
borrows the principals of the cockroach so
that when it starts running,
it is able to traverse these very,
very broken and unstable landscapes.
The first time that that had been
achieved by any legged machine.
We'll move from hexopods to quadrupeds,
four-legged machines, and we'll spend
some time talking about the marvelous
quadrupeds that have been pioneered by
our friends at Boston Dynamics founded by
Marc Raibert, the very person who taught
us about pogo sticking the robots.
We'll spend some time
talking about how Marc and
his engineers have built those
pogo sticks into these quadrupeds.
Finally, we'll introduce bipeds,
and we'll distinguish
between bipeds that have many, many,
many, many degrees of actuated freedom
such as this anthropomorphic
design to the left and
those machines that are much, much more
inspired by the mechanics of running such
as the ATRIAS machine built by Professor
Hurst at Oregon State University.
We will spend a fair bit of
time thinking about how to
take those principles and extract them
away from either the anthropomorphic or
the mere pogo sticking designs into
designs of bodies that are much,
much more versatile but still embody
these pogo sticking dynamical principles.
Here's a leaping machine built by Ms.
Anna Brill with Avik De, in our
GRASP Laboratory over the last year,
showing how to get leaping behaviors
out of a tailed biped that is
called the Jerboa, about which
you'll hear much more in week four.
Welcome to week three.
We're going to spend the week
putting the bodies together and
thinking about how what we learned
about dynamics and controls and
kinematics can begin to inform
our design of behaviors.